<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A discourse concerning generosity</title>
            <author>Somers, John Somers, Baron, 1651-1716.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1693</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 147 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 79 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A60881</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing S4640</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R221638</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99832927</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99832927</idno>
            <idno type="VID">37402</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A60881)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 37402)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2153:21)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A discourse concerning generosity</title>
                  <author>Somers, John Somers, Baron, 1651-1716.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[12], 143, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed by H,. Clark, for James Adamson, at the Angel and Crown in St. Paul's Church-Yard,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1693.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>By John Somers.</note>
                  <note>With a final advertisement page.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Christian life --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-07</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-11</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-11</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:37402:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:37402:1"/>
            <p>A DISCOURSE Concerning <hi>Generoſity.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>H. Clark,</hi> for <hi>Iames Adamſon,</hi> at the <hi>Angel</hi> and <hi>Crown</hi> in St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s Church-Yard, 1693.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb facs="tcp:37402:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:37402:2"/>
            <head>THE PREFACE.</head>
            <p>SInce we find 'tis ſo difficult a thing to engage Men to the ſincere Love and Pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice of Vertue and Good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs; It is but reaſonable that we make uſe of all manner of proper ways and means which may be deemed ſerviceable to that end. No Conſideration that has any weight, ſhould be omitted; nor any fit Argument or Motive left un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>toucht. It is neceſſary to make our Attempts upon all thoſe Principles of the human Nature, from which
<pb facs="tcp:37402:3"/>Men are wont to act, eſpecially thoſe which are of great force and influence upon them; and to of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer ſuch Arguments and Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tives as are ſuited to work upon each of thoſe Principles reſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctively. Some Principles indeed do operate in Men more power<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully than others: But that need not hinder us from endeavouring, by proper Arguments and Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tives, to work upon thoſe which are leſs powerful: Since none of the Principles of Action which Men naturally have, were put in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to them in vain.</p>
            <p>We know that the Affections or Principles of Hope and Fear are of vaſt and univerſal influ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence upon Mens Actions. Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion could not eaſily ſubſiſt with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out an appointment of Rewards and Puniſhments: Nor could the
<pb facs="tcp:37402:3"/>conſideration of Rewards and Pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment have ſuch force upon Men as it has, but that it is ſuit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to operate vehemently upon two powerful Principles in them, to wit, their Hope and Fear. And hence it comes to paſs, that no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing is more effectual to retain Men within the bounds of their Duty, than the proſpect they have of Reward for the obſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and of Puniſhment for the violation of it. And this ſhews, that 'tis upon very good reaſon, that the Scriptures do chiefly ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply and inſiſt on Arguments drawn from this Topick, to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gage Men to Vertue and Piety; and that Divines and Preachers have uſually taken the ſame Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thod. But my Deſign at preſent is of a ſomewhat different nature. And becauſe the Topick of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards
<pb facs="tcp:37402:4"/>and Puniſhments has been; and is, copiouſly and fully treat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed on by Divines: To them I ſhall leave it: To whoſe Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vince it ſeems more eſpecially to belong.</p>
            <p>But beſides Hope and Fear, there are ſome other Principles within us, of which great uſe may be made, in order to engage us to the love and practice of Vertue. Particularly, from the natural ſenſe we have of Honour and Shame, we may likewiſe draw good and forcible Motives to Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue. And by adding the Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tives we draw from them, to thoſe which are wont to be drawn from the other Principles that are in us, we may bring our ſelves under a more powerful Obligation to do our Duty. This is what I propoſe to my ſelf in this Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe.
<pb facs="tcp:37402:4"/>Wherein I do not go a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout to detract from, much leſs wholly to exclude thoſe Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments or Motives which are fetch'd from the conſideration of Rewards and Puniſhments, or from any other juſt Topick: But leaving them upon their own bot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tom, am endeavouring to rein<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>force them with thoſe additional Arguments and Motives which re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſult from the Principles that are in us of Honour and Shame. I would engage Men to Vertue and Goodneſs, by working upon their natural Principles of Self-eſteem and Ambition, and of Honour and Shame: And, therefore, doubt not but I ſhall be thought to act in concert with thoſe, who like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe deſign to engage Men to Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue, by Arguments and Motives calculated to work upon Mens
<pb facs="tcp:37402:5"/>Hope or Fear, or any other of their natural Principles. And ſince Men are of various Diſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitions, and not only different Perſons, but even the ſame Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons at different times, do act up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on various Motives: It may be hoped that the greater variety of juſt Motives are made uſe of, the better ſucceſs may enſue; and that, if the Arguments or Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tives of the one ſort do not take faſt hold of Men, thoſe of the other ſort peradventure may.</p>
            <p>And I confeſs I found my ſelf the more willing to engage my Pen on this Subject, becauſe Generoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty is not uſually taken notice of ſo much as, perhaps, it ought, and I conceive deſerves to be. There is but little mention (for ought I can find) made of it, either in the Syſtems of Moraliſts, or the
<pb facs="tcp:37402:5"/>Inſtructions of ordinary Precep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors and Tutors. And that, if I am not miſtaken, is a defect ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary to be in ſome meaſure ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plied: Since Generoſity is a Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciple extreamly uſeful, and of ſo very extenſive a Nature, that it does in a ſort pervade the whole Body of Morality; as I hope to ſhew by and by.</p>
            <p>In the mean time, I think my ſelf obliged to acknowledge, That I am indebted to the Learned and Ingenious <hi>Des Cartes,</hi> for that which is indeed the Ground-work of this Eſſay. I have followed as exactly as I could, the lively, tho' ſhort Deſcription which he has given of Generoſity; and ſome times chuſe to make uſe of his words, not being able to find o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers better, or indeed ſo good. But whether I have improved any
<pb facs="tcp:37402:6"/>of the Hints which he has given, or repreſented them to advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage; that I muſt ſubmit to the Judgment of others; ſince it is neither needful nor proper for me to determine in the Caſe.</p>
            <p>The Argument it ſelf, I muſt confeſs, is great and noble; and requires a better Head and Genius than I am Maſter of, to handle it juſtly. But if I have attempt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed a thing above my Pitch; I am ſure I have done it with a good Intention. Nor can I, upon the Matter, blame my ſelf for the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ndertaking: Since the cauſe of Vertue ſeems to demand an At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt of this nature; and the Perſons beſt qualified have not (that I know) engaged in it ſo fully and particularly as might be wiſh'd. <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>pon that Account, I am perſuaded, the Sincerity of
<pb facs="tcp:37402:6"/>my intention in this Matter (which I ſteadfaſtly avow, and of which I believe there will be no reaſon to doubt) will entitle me to the Excuſe of candid People for the meanneſs of my Perform<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance. And I allow my ſelf to hope, that as courſe as the Picture is which I preſent you with, it will ſerve to make the Original appear very Amiable.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="imprimatur">
            <pb facs="tcp:37402:7"/>
            <p>Imprimatur,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Ra. Barker, <hi>Reveren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſſimo in Chriſto Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tri ac D<hi rend="sup">no.</hi> D<hi rend="sup">no.</hi>
                  </hi> Jo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hanni <hi>Archiepiſcopo</hi> Cant. <hi>a Sacris.</hi>
               </signed>
               <date>
                  <hi>Feb.</hi> 15, 1692/3.</date>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="tract">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:37402:7"/>
            <head>A DISCOURSE Concerning Generoſity.</head>
            <p>WE live in an Age where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in there are great pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenſions made to Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, and no leſs to Honour. And as theſe two are in themſelves excellent Things, ſo I muſt confeſs 'tis a great ſatisfaction to me, that they continue to bear ſo general a Reputation in the World. It cannot indeed be won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred, that Things which are both excellent in their Nature, and like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:37402:8"/>of univerſal Eſteem, ſhould be the Objects of moſt Mens aim and ambition; ſince its very natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral, it ſhould be ſo. But if Men were as well agreed, what is moſt truly and properly meant by the Terms, Religion and Honour, as they are agreed, that theſe two things deſerve their Eſteem and Proſecution; we might hope for ſome viſible Improvements both in their Sentiments and Practice.</p>
            <p>It is our misfortune, that we are too often carried away by Appear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ances; and calling things by wrong Names, are inſenſibly led into er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour, whilſt we think our ſelves altogether in the right. We apply to ſome things the characters that are due to others, and give magnifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent Names to things that are, in their nature, either vitious and faul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, or at beſt but trivial and incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderable. Thus it ſometimes falls out, that Men call that by the name of Religion, which either is not
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:37402:8"/>Religion, or which at beſt has but little to do with it; and by the name of Honour, that which either is not ſo, or which, at beſt, ſcarce de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerves to be conſidered under that Title. Now he that has, in this manner, entertained miſtaken No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions about either Religion, on the one hand, or about Honour on the other, is neerly concerned to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctifie ſuch Miſtakes; and that, for one plain Reaſon, among others, to wit, Becauſe the abuſe of a very good thing commonly produces very ill effects.</p>
            <p>It is not my deſign to enter into a large Diſquiſition upon the Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects of Religion and Honour; I muſt content my ſelf to touch on them incidently, ſo far as they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late to my preſent Argument: In the proſecution whereof, I hope nevertheleſs, to make ſome advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage of the univerſal Eſteem which theſe two have juſtly obtained in the World. And ſince Generoſity has a
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:37402:9"/>natural Affinity both to Religion and to Honour, I ſuppoſe a Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe upon that Subject, will be thought the more ſuitable to the Genius of the Times. But, which is of much greater Importance, it may likewiſe be hoped, that the Man of Religion will be induced to entertain the better thoughts of Honour; and on the other hand, the Man of Honour, to entertain the better thoughts of Religion, when they ſhall reſpectively conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, that theſe two have, in them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, a natural Relation and Affi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity to each other, at how great di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance ſoever the opinion or pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice of ſome Men may ſeem to have ſet them. For I am perſuaded, it will be no hard matter to reconcile theſe two, if we will but reſolve them into their firſt and naked Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples, and will but take the pains to ſeparate each from its abuſes and the falſe characters attributed to it: Which being the only occaſion of
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:37402:9"/>the ſeeming difference, as ſoon as thoſe are removed, that ſeeming difference will vaniſh, and the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural agreement there is between them will ſhew it ſelf. That there is really ſuch an agreement between them, will, I hope, be made out in the proceſs of this Diſcourſe; at leaſt ſo far as may be neceſſary to my preſent purpoſe; which I ſhall think ſufficient.</p>
            <p>When I ſpeak of a conformity or agreement between Religion and Honour, it is evident I don't mean by Religion, particular modes or diſtinctions of Religion, or di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinctions of Sects or Profeſſions, which are ſometimes call'd by that Name; nor do I mean by Honour, temporal Dignity or height of Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle or Station, ancienty of Family, right of Precedence or Jurisdiction, Gentility, or any of thoſe external Gallantries that are wont to make ſuch a glare in the Eyes of the World; which are likewiſe ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:37402:10"/>called by the name of Honour. There is indeed difference enough between Religion and Honour taken reſpectively in theſe Senſes. But by Religion I mean, the Law of the rational Nature, or the complex of theſe Laws which are given by God Almighty unto Mankind for the Government of their Lives and Actions. And by Honour, I mean, That Principle reſiding in Mens minds, by which they are excited to chuſe and do thoſe things which are really worthy and becoming, and to refuſe and avoid thoſe which are really baſe and unbecoming: Which Principle, becauſe it gives Men the genuine ſtamp of Honour, is rightly called by that name. And it is between theſe two, taken re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpectively in the latter ſenſe, that I affirm there is ſuch a Conformity: I mean a Conformity between the Rule of Religion, and the Rule of Honour; and between the Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciple of Religion and the Principle of Honour.</p>
            <pb n="7" facs="tcp:37402:10"/>
            <p>If we look into the Compoſure of Mankind, we ſhall find that they are naturally endowed with a Principle of Self-love. And this Principle is found to be of vaſt and univerſal influence upon them, and the ſecret Spring as it were of all their Acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons. Now one effect of this Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciple is, That it diſpoſes Men to value themſelves for ſomething or other, and to a certain ambition or deſire of having thoſe Qualities or doing thoſe Actions which they ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count great and admirable. This may be called Self eſteem: And is a Principle which operates variouſly in different Perſons, according to their different Application of it, and the different Conceptions which they have of things: Inſomuch that it carries ſome Men into an infinite number of Follies, whilſt it proves to others who make the right uſe of it, a Spur to brave and worthy Actions and Deſigns: Of which more in its place.</p>
            <pb n="8" facs="tcp:37402:11"/>
            <p>If any Man think, that all man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of Self-eſteem is vitious and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnable; he may pleaſe to conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, that what I here call Self-eſteem taken in a Philoſophical ſenſe, is a Principle which we have unavoid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ably, without our own Choice: It neceſſarily reſults from the general Principle of Self-love fundamental<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly implanted in us by Nature, and is far different from what is ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narily called Self-conceit. Thoſe Principles or Diſpoſitions which we have in us by Nature, ought not, when conſidered only in their pure Naturals to be deemed culpable; left thereby we obliquely accuſe the Author and Lord of Nature him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf. It is univerſally allowed by conſidering Men, that the Affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons which are put in us by Nature, ſuch as Love, Hate, Deſire, Joy, Grief, and the like, are in them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves innocent and inculpable; and that 'tis only the exceſs and abuſe which renders them vitious. It is
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:37402:11"/>not our Fault, that we have in us the Affections of Love or Hate, for that we have naturally and una<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voidably: But our Fault is, that we Love or Hate undue Objects, or Love or Hate immoderately. So it is not our Fault that we have in us the Affection of Self-eſteem; for that we have alſo unavoidably from Nature it ſelf, ſo that 'tis impoſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to erace it out of our minds: But our Fault is in miſapplying this Affection, by eſteeming our ſelves without juſt cauſe, or by doing it to exceſs; in which caſe, we fall into Pride, Self-conceit, and the like Vices, which are juſtly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned by all Mankind.</p>
            <p>Since, therefore, there is put in Man, by Nature, ſuch an Affection or Principle of Self-eſteem; and ſince it is of ſuch vaſt influence upon his thoughts and actions, it muſt needs be of huge importance to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gulate this Affection rightly, ſo that it may be applyed to juſt Objects
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:37402:12"/>and exerted in a juſt manner: Eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially conſidering, that 'tis as bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficial to uſe it right, as 'tis pernici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous and dangerous to abuſe or miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>apply it. But we need not think, that we are under any obligation to endeavour to extirpate this Princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple or Affection out of our minds, any more than we are, thoſe of Love, Deſire, Joy, Grief, Hope, Fear, and ſuch like; we are not obliged to things impoſſible: But we are under the ſtrongeſt Obliga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions in the World, to endeavour to correct in them whatever tends to abuſe or exceſs: And this is not only poſſible, but is indeed one of the grand buſineſſes of our Life. As for the Affection of Self-eſteem, I am perſuaded, the Vertue or Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciple of Generoſity, which I am a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout to treat of, will be of great uſe to regulate it, and I think I may ſay, without fallacy, moſt of the other Affections too.</p>
            <pb n="11" facs="tcp:37402:12"/>
            <p>Now in handling the preſent Argument, I ſhall endeavour to do theſe three things.</p>
            <list>
               <item>
                  <hi>First,</hi> To explain the Nature of Generoſity.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Secondly,</hi> To ſhew the uſefulneſs of the Principle, for the due go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment of our Actions.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Thirdly,</hi> To ſhew how Genero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity may be acquired, or afterwards improved in our Minds.</item>
            </list>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt,</hi> I ſhall try to ſhew the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of Generoſity. Now Genero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity may, in general, be conſidered under a twofold reſpect, 1. As a Paſſion or Affection in Man; and this is the more narrow and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrained Notion of it. And next, As a Power or Principle immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ately founded in the rational Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture; and this is the more large and comprehenſive Notion of it. So far as it is attended with a Commotion in the Blood and Spirits, or with a Senſation more immediately rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting to the Body, ſo far it has the
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:37402:13"/>nature of a Paſſion or Affection. And ſo far as it depends purely on the rational Nature of a Man, and is attended with ſuch Cogitations as immediately relate to the Soul, ſo far it may be conſidered as an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tellectual or rational Power. Nor need we think it ſtrange, that hav<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing but one Name, it ſhould, under different reſpects, have the nature of an Affection, and likewiſe of an intellectual Power. The Names we give to things are not always ade<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quate; and its ſcarce poſſible they ſhould be in Matters of this kind. There is ſo ſtrict an Union betwixt the Soul and Body of Man, and ſuch a reciprocal operation of the one upon the other, that ſundry of his Acts are compounded, partly of Senſations referring to the Animal Nature, and partly of Cogitations referring to the Rational. Since, therefore, thoſe Cogitations of the Soul, which either produce a Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue in Man or accompany it, are in
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:37402:13"/>moſt Caſes either attended with or confirmed by ſome Perception or Affection of the Animal Nature: And ſince, on the other hand, ſome Perfections or Affections of the Ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mal Nature diſpoſe the Soul to cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain Cogitations helpful to the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducing in it the acts of ſome parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular Vertues: It is eaſie to believe, there will be in the effect of this re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciprocal Operation, a mixture of the Vertue and Affection; and ſo we find it falls out. Humility is a known Vertue, and Pride a known Vice; yet each of theſe are in ſome ſenſe a Paſſion or Affection, as well as upon other accounts a Vertue and a Vice. Humility, for inſtance, has the nature of a Vertue, ſo far as it is a Power or Principle referring purely to the Soul, and producing ſuch Cogitations and Actions as are commendable by the Laws of the rational Nature; but is ſtill a Paſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on or Affection, ſo far as it is ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>companied with a commotion in the
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:37402:14"/>animal Spirits, or in general with any corporeal Impreſſion. The like might be ſaid of ſeveral other Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues; and, <hi>mutatis mutandis,</hi> of ſeveral Vices.</p>
            <p>Generoſity then, conſidered as an Affection, conſiſts in a juſt Self-eſteem, whereby a Man values him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf juſt ſo much as he lawfully and fairly may. And under this reſpect it is a Species of the general Affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, called Admiration, and holds the Medium between the two Paſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of vitious Humility and Pride, correcting what is amiſs in each. But there are likewiſe certain other Diſpoſitions or Habitudes (worth remarking, becauſe they are of great uſe and ornament) which may be referred to Generoſity; of which ſort are, a maſculine Firm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and Conſtancy, Preſence of Mind and Sweetneſs of Temper. This Firmneſs and Conſtancy is of force to compoſe a Mans Spirits, to eſtabliſh his Thoughts, and to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:37402:14"/>him ſteady and conſiſtent with himſelf; and by thoſe means ſecures him, not only from many of the Livities and Imbecilities which they are apt to fall into, who are guided by impulſe and fortuitous impreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; but alſo, from ſeveral of thoſe errors and prepoſterous act<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings to which fear or feebleneſs of Spirit are wont to expoſe Men. And ſo Preſence of Mind, operates in much the ſame manner, in caſe of ſudden emergencies; and by pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerving the mind intrepid, undi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſturbed, and preſent to it ſelf on ſuch occaſions, ſecures the Man from being ſurprized into things hurtful or indecent. So, likewiſe, the Sweetneſs of Temper which ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>companies Generoſity, ſerves to render Men pacifick, agreeable and eaſie to themſelves and others. And as it tends to overcome the humor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous and ſour Qualities which make Men uneaſie to themſelves, and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>agreeable in Converſation; ſo it
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:37402:15"/>likewiſe diſpoſes them to all the decent Expreſſions imaginable of Civility and Complaiſance.</p>
            <p>It is true, the ſeveral Diſpoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons aforeſaid may be many times owing to Mens natural Tempera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. But yet, if Men have them not by the gift of Nature, 'tis in great meaſure within their power to acquire them, or to cultivate and improve them when acquired; and to correct the contrary Quali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties. Some Men indeed have the happineſs to be naturally of an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>genuous Diſpoſition, Candid, Sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cere, Modeſt, and of a firm and maſculine Temper; having, by the particular vouchſafement of God Almighty, a lovelineſs and ſweet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of Spirit which cannot be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs'd, and ſuch a Command over their Spirits as is of extraordinary advantage to them. They who have theſe and the like Qualities implanted in them by Nature, are in a ſort born to Generoſity. And
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:37402:15"/>even they who have them in a low<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er degree, are altogether unexcuſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble if they do not endeavour to cheriſh and improve them, ſince the acquiſition of Generoſity would be ſo eaſie, where there is ſuch a na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural aptitude for it. On the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary, ſome Men are particularly unhappy in their compoſure, being naturally of a rough and feral Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, dark and ſolitary in their Minds, ſtubborn, haughty, or of feeble and impotent Spirits. He who is concerned in any of theſe or ſuch like ill Qualities (for one cannot with a good Grace ſuppoſe them all in one Man) is, its true, under peculiar difficulties as to the acquiring of Generoſity. But as that ought to quicken his diligence and care to overcome thoſe Impe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diments which his natural Temper puts him under, ſo if he does over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come them, his Conqueſt will be the more glorious: But I am not to inſiſt upon that in this place. But
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:37402:16"/>from the different Diſpoſitions of People, we may obſerve in what manner Generoſity reſides in Mens Tempers, and how it mixes it ſelf with their other Affections and Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſitions. And this, I think, does partly tend to ſhew the Nature of it; which is what we have been conſidering.</p>
            <p>But ſince my deſign is, to conſider Generoſity, not barely as it falls un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the notion of a Paſſion or Affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction; but principally, as it is a Vertue or intellectual Power inhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent in the Mind, under which re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect it is of the greateſt uſe: I muſt now advance a little further. Now if Generoſity be (as I hope to ſhew that it is) an intellectual Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of the Soul, helpful for the good government of a Mans Paſſions, cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poreal Impreſſions and Appetites, and diſpoſing him to proſecute that which is abſolutely beſt (which is the character and deſcription of Vertue) then we ſhall be obliged,
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:37402:16"/>in reaſon, to acknowledge it to be a Vertue. And if, moreover, it be (as indeed it is) ſuch an intellectual Power of the Soul, as ſerves to produce in Men the habit and pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice of ſeveral particular Vertues; then it will rather fall under the notion of a general Principle of Vertue, than of a particular Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue. And as ſuch, chiefly, I mean now to conſider it; not ſingly as a particular Vertue, but in a larger extent, as 'tis a general Principle of the rational Nature, and the fruitful Parent of many particular Vertues.</p>
            <p>But before I proceed further up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on this Matter, it will, I conceive, be proper to premiſe a few ſumma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Conſiderations, for clearing the way to what follows. It is ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledged by all Men, who are in their right Mind, That there is an eſſential difference between Good and Evil; a difference founded in the nature of things, ſo that ſome
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:37402:17"/>things are eſſentially Good, and others eſſentially Evil: That what is Good, is Eligible, Honourable and becoming Mans Nature, and tends to advance and perfect it: And on the contrary, that what is Evil, is to be refuſed and avoided, is diſhonourable and misbecoming, and tends to a Man's Shame, Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach and Miſery. That what is Good, naturally imports in it the character of Honourable, that is, challenges and deſerves Honour; and the doing of it, cannot be mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of juſt ſhame or diſgrace to a Man: And on the contrary, that what is Evil, naturally imports in it the character of Diſhonourable, and the doing of it, cannot be mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of juſt praiſe or ornament to a Man. And that Mankind are en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dued with Notions correſponding to the nature of things in this caſe; and have, by the Principles inhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent in their minds, an ability of diſcerning, in ſome meaſure, what
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:37402:17"/>is Good and what Evil, what is Honourable and Becoming, and what is Diſhonourable and Unbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coming. Theſe things are clear in themſelves; and they are likewiſe confirmed to us by the univerſal conſent of wiſe Men, who have, in all Ages, eſteemed ſome things Good, and others Evil: The for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer they have accounted Great, Worthy and Honourable; the latter, Baſe, Raſcally and Diſhonourable. Hence they have called Vertue, an <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, that is, a Reſemblance or Conformity to God, that which is Fit, Equitable, Becoming, Beautiful, Divine, and the like; giving the contrary Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pellations to Vice. Hence they al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways deemed the former worthy of Eſteem, Veneration and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward; and the latter, worthy of Shame, Contempt and Puniſhment. And hence ſuch Perſons as have been endowed with extraordinary
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:37402:18"/>Qualifications, and have done great and worthy things, have been in all Ages thought to deſerve Eſteem and Honour: But on the contrary, ſuch as have been vitious and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>praved in their Minds, or guilty of baſe and infamous Actions, have been thought to deſerve Shame and Ignominy. And upon ſuch Princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples as theſe, is founded the very notion of Merit, which implies in it, as well the ſuitableneſs and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gruity there is, that ſuch as have brave Spirits, and perform brave and worthy things, ſhould be ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noured and eſteemed, as likewiſe the right and title they have to ſuch Honour and Eſteem, as the juſt reward of their Vertue. And hence all wiſe Lawgivers have thought it both neceſſary and juſt, to appoint Honours and Rewards for vertuous and heroical Actions: and Shame and Puniſhments for vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious and infamous ones. The foregoing Conſiderations amount to
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:37402:18"/>this, That nothing can be truly and intrinſically Honourable, but what is according to Vertue: That what is according to Vertue, is truly and intrinſically Honourable: That Praiſe and Honour are by a natural and indelible Right due to true Merit; and true Merit is founded only in true Vertue and Goodneſs. Thus it may be ſeen, what is moſt truly honourable and conducing to our Happineſs, and the Perfection of our Nature. And in regard we have in us, by Nature, a vehement deſire of Happineſs and Perfection, it highly concerns us to make uſe of that Principle for the purpoſes which God Almighty appears to have deſigned in his im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>planting it in us; that ſo we do not abuſe or pervert a Principle which is given us for excellent ends, and which is of mighty in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluence upon our Minds and Acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and put upon our ſelves the fatal Cheat of purſuing an imagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:37402:19"/>Good, and an imaginary Felicity, inſtead of that which is real and ſolid: But on the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary, being made ſenſible in what our true Honour and Happineſs conſiſt, we may proſecute that with our utmoſt intention and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligence. And how ſerviceable the Principle of Generoſity may be to us in that good Deſign, may be worth our while to enquire.</p>
            <p>Now I come to ſpeak of Genero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity, as it is founded in, or more immediately relates to the rational Nature. And under this Notion it may, in like manner as before, be conſidered, firſt, with reſpect to the Principle of Self-eſteem, and then with reſpect to thoſe other Qualifications or Powers of the ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tional Nature, which it either pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duces or is wont to be attended withal. So that being now to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe of it as an intellectual Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciple, I muſt be allowed to take it in a fuller Latitude than I have yet
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:37402:19"/>done, or could properly do when I conſider'd it barely as a Paſſion or Affection. And after I have ſpoken ſomething concerning the Princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of Self-eſteem, I ſhall endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour to ſhew, how Generoſity is ſuited to regulate and conduct it rightly, and then ſhall take notice of ſome particular Vertues which belong, or may be referred to the character of Generoſity.</p>
            <p>Tho' the Principle of Self-eſteem be common to all Men, being im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>planted in them by Nature, yet it is found to operate diverſly in dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent Perſons, and even in the ſame Perſon at different times. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of a very lively and moving Nature, it will exert it ſelf one way or other, either for better or worſe. If it be not made an Inſtrument to Vertue, it will prove an Inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to Vice; and for want of being rightly managed and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducted, will carry Men into thoſe Extreams which are vitious and
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:37402:20"/>culpable. Thus it has very diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent Effects, according as Men uſe it rightly or amiſs. As, when a Man reflecting inwardly upon him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, ſuffers the Self-eſteem that is in him to work upon falſe grounds or to exceed its juſt limits, and either imagines that he has in him thoſe good Qualities which he real<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly has not, or ſwells beyond due bounds thoſe good Qualities which are really in him; and thereupon ſets a higher value upon himſelf than in Juſtice and Reaſon he ought; or unjuſtly prefers himſelf before other Men: Then that Self-eſteem which was in its pure Natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rals an innocent Affection, degene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rates into Pride, and becomes juſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly blameable. And on the other hand, when a Man reflecting upon himſelf, from the contemplation he has of his own Imbecillities, and of his inability to conduct his Paſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and Actions aright, is depreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed in his Thoughts for want of
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:37402:20"/>ſirmneſs and ſteadineſs of Mind, aggravates his own Imperfections, and depretiates what is really com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendable in him; and thereupon ſets a lower value upon himſelf, at leaſt while this Paſſion continues, than in reaſon he ought: Then his Self-eſteem (if one may here ſo call it) degenerates into vitious Humi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity or Abjectneſs; which is like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe blameable. But in oppoſition to both theſe, when upon the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flection a Man makes on himſelf, he ſets ſuch a value upon himſelf as is no more or leſs than what is juſt and warrantable, and poiſes his Mind between the extreams of Pride and Abjectneſs; then his Self-eſteem is rightly tempered and conducted, and the Man is led to that Temper of Mind which is the character of Generoſity.</p>
            <p>It will be readily acknowledged, that 'tis much more frequent for Men to err by eſteeming themſelves over-much, than by ſinking their
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:37402:21"/>own value. For though Self-con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt, as well as Pride, proceeds from the operation of Self-love, the former being compounded of Self-love, Admiration and Grief, for the defects which a Man finds or ſuppoſes to be in him; as the latter is compouned of Self-love, Admiration and Joy, for the Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellencies he finds or ſuppoſes to be in him: Yet the Self-love that is in Men, does, as it falls out, more eaſily and readily produce Self-e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteem than Self contempt. There is a ſtronger Byaſs on that ſide than on the other. And therefore 'tis no wonder that Pride, which is a kind of Self-eſteem, to wit, a wrongful or exceſſive one, ſhould be a more common Error than viti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Humility which is a kind of Self-contempt. Nor will it ſeem ſtrange, that Pride ſhould be the more growing and thriving Vice of the two, if it be conſider'd, that the Self-love that is in Men has not
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:37402:21"/>only the greater Byaſs towards Pride, but likewiſe operates more vehemently that way; which may eaſily occaſion that Vice to ſpread further, and run more into the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tream: As when a thing is moving, the ſtronger its Motion is, the fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther it is like to run beyond the Lines. Upon which account, it ſeems neceſſary, for Men to guard them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves with the greater care and cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion on that ſide where there is the greater danger. But ſince I am not adviſing any Body, either to over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate himſelf for fear of falling into a vitious Humility, or to under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate himſelf for fear of falling into Pride; but am endeavouring to point at a Method for avoiding both thoſe extreams: I ſhall think it ſufficient for my preſent purpoſe to obſerve, That both thoſe Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treams are condemnable; and that Generoſity is a Remedy againſt both.</p>
            <pb n="30" facs="tcp:37402:22"/>
            <p>But in the mean time, is it really a diſadvantage and ſnare to us, that we are naturally more diſpoſed to Eſteem than Diſ-eſteem our ſelves? Or, may not that natural Diſpoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion be ſo tempered and applyed as to be of great advantage to us? If it be a diſadvantage and ſnare to us, it becomes ſo through our own fault; and if it be not made uſe of to our greater advantage and bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit, it will likewiſe be our own fault. The diſpoſition to eſteem our ſelves, is ſtrong and weighing; but what is its natural tendency and uſe? Is it the natural uſe of it, to encline us to eſteem our ſelves upon falſe or frivolous Grounds, or to eſteem our ſelves beyond the juſt meaſure? Is the natural uſe of it to lead us to Pride, and the nu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merous train of hateful and black qualities that are wont to accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany it? Certainly it cannot be. Theſe are Faults which proceed from the groſs abuſe of this diſpoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:37402:22"/>and therefore cannot be the natural uſe of it. Or is it deſigned only to give us the fantaſtick plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of Self-applauſe? Sure this is too low and mean a Deſign for a Principle of ſo great and univerſal influence as this is upon our thoughts and actions. On the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary, without doubt the natural uſe and deſign of it is, To beget in Men an emulation and ambition for Vertue, to eſtabliſh and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe their Minds; and in a word, to incite them to worthy and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coming things, and deter them from the contrary. If Men were void of all Self-eſteem, they could not be touch'd with the ſenſe either of Honour or Shame. Theſe would take no hold of them, ſince they are founded upon the eſteem which Men have of themſelves, and cannot ſubſiſt without it. Now the im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſions of Honour and Shame are found to lay a great Reſtraint upon Mankind; and ſometimes work
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:37402:23"/>upon them, when other Conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions prove ineffectual. But if Men were deſtitute of all Self-eſteem, they would be looſe from this Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtraint; which I think 'tls clear would be a great diſadvantage to them: And therefore ſure 'tis an advantage to them to have ſuch a Principle. So likewiſe, ſince Men are ſo naturally diſpoſed to eſteem themſelves; that both may and ought to be an Argument to them, to undertake and do thoſe things only which are really Praiſe-wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy. Seeing they love and are willing to have eſteem; that is a proper Motive to them to do thoſe things which may deſerve and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure it. But the Self-eſteem that is in Men, is alſo of uſe, as it ſerves to compoſe and eſtabliſh their Minds. It brings with it a calm and ſerenity into the Mind, and puts it, as one may ſay, into a good Humour. It produces in Men ſuch Sentiments as give them a ſtea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dineſs
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:37402:23"/>and aſſurance of Mind, and ſecure them from the diſorder and embaraſs which the Affection of Self-contempt is wont to be at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended with. And it is likewiſe of great force to animate and enliven the Mind, and to diſpoſe Men to action and effort. For being in its operation, mixed with a kind of Joy and Complacency, the ſenſati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons that are thereby produced in the Man, ſerve to open his thoughts, and to diſpoſe him to a lively and active temper of Mind: Which is of conſiderable uſe. Whereas on the other hand, the Affection of Self-deſpect tends to deaden and diſcompoſe the Mind; and being in its operation mixed with the ſluggiſh and melancholy Paſſion of Grief (as I before obſerved) brings upon the Mind ſuch a Languor as is oftentimes very prejudicial. So that ſeems in it ſelf rather be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neficial it than hurtful to Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind, that they have ſuch a natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:37402:24"/>Byaſs and Diſpoſition to Self-eſteem.</p>
            <p>But you will ſay, this Self-eſteem is apt to exceed its juſt bounds, and to betray Men into Pride and an extravagant conceit of themſelves. But is it therefore in it ſelf culpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble? If it be miſchievous in its A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buſe, may it not be advantagious in its right and regular uſe? If it pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce this effect in us, it does not (as I have already ſaid) do this na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turally and unavoidably, but by ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cident and by our own Fault. There are ſeveral Principles or Propenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties that belong to our Nature, which will certainly run into ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treams if they be not ballanced and rightly managed; eſpecially thoſe which are, as this is, vehement and of powerful influence upon us. And if we are not wont to think that they are in themſelves culpable and unmanageable, why ſhould we think this to be ſo? Let us turn our Eyes but to a few Inſtances.
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:37402:24"/>Every Body knows we have in us a Principle of Self-preſervation: Which is indeed both innocent in it ſelf, and alſo of great and ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary uſe. But this is likewiſe apt to exceed its juſt bounds. If Men ſhould give it a loſe Rein and follow without reſerve its blind Dictates, it would in all probabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity throw them into ſuch an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs of Fear and Solicitude for them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, as would render them uſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs to their Friends or their Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try, as would diſable them to pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſue the Rules of Juſtice, Charity, Fortitude and all other Vertues, the practice whereof may be at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended with danger and hazard, and would perhaps ſometimes de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy the very end for which this Principle ſeems deſigned, as it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>falls them, who hurl themſelves in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Danger or Death, through ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſive Fear of it and Solicitude to avoid it. There is alſo in Men a vehement deſire of Procreation.
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:37402:25"/>And that Propenſity is innocent in it ſelf, and both may and ought to be ſo governed, as to anſwer its end without exceeding the juſt bounds. Yet ſhould Men let them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves looſe to follow its impulſe without fear or wit, no doubt but it would carry them into the laſt Extravagancies. So likewiſe the innate deſire of Happineſs that is in Men, is capable of being dire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted rightly; and we ought to make uſe of it, as may be ſubſervi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent to the end for which it was given us. But Men may miſapply it; and when they do ſo, it will, by the prevailing influence it has upon them, carry them far into the Extream, and inſpire them with as great a Fervency in the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecution of a falſe or imaginary Good, as of the real and true One. In ſhort, theſe and other vehement and operative Principles or Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſities are given Men for wiſe and good Purpoſes; ſome of which
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:37402:25"/>we are able eaſily to diſcover, and if they be rightly managed will be of great uſe. But if we do not en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour to conduct them by our Reaſon and the Laws which God hath given us for that purpoſe, the blame will juſtly fall upon our own ſelves. It will not therefore, I conceive, either turn to ſo good account, or ſo well become us, to bequarrel and find fault with our own Nature and Compoſure, as it will, to endeavour all we can to at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temper and conduct the Principles and Propenſities that are in us, by the Laws of Reaſon and Revela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. But I am now concerned on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly with the Principle of Self eſteem, and therefore ſhall proceed to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider, how it is mixed with Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roſity, and conducted by it.</p>
            <p>Whoſo exactly obſerves the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of Mankind, will find, that there is nothing which can ſo properly and abſolutely be called a Man's own, as the free diſpoſal of his
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:37402:26"/>own Will: And that generally ſpeaking, a Man cannot juſtly be either praiſed or diſpraiſed, but for thoſe Actions which depend on this freedom of his Nature: becauſe he has nothing elſe ſo entirely in his own power. Now agreeably hereto, the Character of a Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous Man will be ſuch as fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lows:</p>
            <p>The Generous Man finds in him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf a Reſolution to uſe that Free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of his Will rightly, and thereupon is always enclined to undertake and execute what he ſhall judge beſt and moſt fitting to be done. And then, he values him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf upon nothing ſo much as upon the ſincere uſe of his Natural Free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, and the firm purpoſes he makes to proſecute Vertue with an extream application. He does not value himſelf upon account of any of thoſe things which are wont to beget Pride in Men, ſuch as Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours, Riches, Wit, Beauty, Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs,
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:37402:26"/>or the like: but upon account of that, which no Man can, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perly ſpeaking, be proud of, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it is not an Excellency pecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liar to himſelf above other Men, but a Property of the Human Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture in general, to wit, The Free Diſpoſal of his own Will. And by this means he is ſecured from Pride. On the other hand, he is very ſenſible of the Failings and Imperfections incident to Human Nature, by reaſon whereof he knows himſelf to be liable to thoſe Errours and Offences which he ſees in other Men. And he conſiders at the ſame time, that other Men, as having the free diſpoſal of their own Wills, as well as himſelf has of his, may uſe that freedom as well as himſelf does or better, if they be not themſelves in fault. And therefore he is not enclined to entertain big thoughts of himſelf, or to prefer himſelf before other Men. And this preſerves him in
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:37402:27"/>an humble and modeſt temper of Mind. But in regard he finds in himſelf (as I have ſaid) a ſteady Purpoſe of uſing his Natural Free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom rightly, and of doing always, as near as he can, that which is really and abſolutely beſt, which he thinks is the main thing that gives Men a real value or worth: He is ſatisfied, that he ought not to be contemned though he want ſeveral of thoſe External Conſiderations for which Men are generally valued in the World, ſuch as Honours, Wealth, Beauty, or the like. Nor does he much care if he be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temned for the want of them. Much leſs is he concerned, if he fortune to be diſvalued for a defect in ſome of thoſe trivial things, which in the opinion of ſome People paſs for Recommendations of a Man; ſuch as Garb, Air, Mien, Accent, or the like. And thus he is placed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove the reach of Contempt, and ſecured from a vicious Humility or
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:37402:27"/>abjectneſs of Spirit. And when he ſurveys, (according to the beſt of his skill, be it greater or leſs) both the Human Nature in general, and Himſelf in particular, he becomes ſenſible, that he has no abſolute need of any thing which it is not in his own power, by the help of God, to acquire and keep. And therefore he is not much diſquieted, though he want ſeveral of the Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naments and Accommodations of Life which others have. Thus, if he have not thoſe External Things which Men are ordinarily valued for, he does not upon that account think himſelf much inferiour to thoſe that have them: And if he have, he does not think himſelf ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periour upon that account, to thoſe that have them not. He has a low va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lue for External things; and is per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded, that the poſſeſſion of them cannot juſtly advance, or the want of them juſtly ſink a Man's real Price. And therefore in eſtimating either
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:37402:28"/>himſelf or others, he is ſatisfied, that theſe or any other things ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trinſical to a Man, or which de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pend on the circumſtances of Mens Life and Fortunes, or for which they muſt be entirely beholden to other Men, ought not to be brought to account. And by ſuch Conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations as theſe he regulates the Self-eſteem that is in him, and makes uſe of it for good purpoſes.</p>
            <p>He is likewiſe perſuaded it would be againſt the Rules of Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice, to value another Man either beneath or above what we know to be his juſt Deſert; and that for the ſame Reaſons it would be againſt Juſtice to do ſo by himſelf. And this is another Conſideration by which he regulates the Self-eſteem that is in him, and comes to think of himſelf as near as he can, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther more nor leſs than he lawfully and fairly may. But as he is care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful not to undertake another, through Envy, Hatred or other ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:37402:28"/>Motive; ſo he is likewiſe careful not to over-value himſelf, out of Partiality and Self-love: But in the judgment he paſſes either on himſelf or others, endeavours to make all thoſe allowances which Reaſon and Juſtice require. And tho' he does not take any more de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light than other Men in the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>templation of himſelf, and is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved to make no other uſe of that Self eſteem which he has in him, than only to eſtabliſh his Mind, and excite him to the more vigorous proſecution of that which is Beſt and moſt Honourable; yet when a neceſſary or juſt occaſion is offered for his paſſing a judgment upon himſelf in this nature, then he falls into ſuch cogitations as carry him even between Pride and Abjectneſs, and ſecure him from the Errors of both.</p>
            <p>Agreeably hereunto, from the conſideration of the Dignity of the rational Nature, and of the Obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gations
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:37402:29"/>that ariſe from thence to act ſuitably to that Character, the generous Man finds himſelf obliged to make a firm and conſtant Reſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution, not to do any thing that is diſhonourable or unbecoming. The juſt apprehenſions he has touching his own Nature, reſtrain him from doing thoſe things which are, in the concurrent judgment of wiſe Men, baſe and ignominious; and excite him to whatever is ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent and praiſe-worthy. When he conſiders the character which Mankind bear in the Creation, how that they are placed in a middle rank between the Angelical and the Brutal Nature: This ſuggeſts to him, that it is unbecoming and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neath him, to ſink himſelf to a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formity with the latter; and that 'tis no leſs worthy of his care and ambition, to aſpire after a ſimili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude to the former (as far as may conſiſt with the impotency of his Nature) by a juſt obſervation of
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:37402:29"/>thoſe Laws which the ſupream Cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ator has given the rational World to govern themſelves by. And therefore he thinks, 'tis for his Credit and Honour to do thoſe things which tend to advance his Nature, as on the t'other hand 'tis a ſhame and diſgrace to him, to do thoſe things which tend to debaſe it. But though he have in his Breaſt an extream ſenſe of Honour, yet that does not operate within him as a fantaſtical airy Principle, but as a Spur to vertuous and wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy Actions: For he is far from the empty humour of Popularity or Vain-glory, and places true Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, not in the little niceties or punctilio's of pretended Reputati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and Gallantry, but in thoſe things which will recommend him to God and good Men, and which import a real and ſolid Worth. And when (to carry this Conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration a little further) he calls to mind the Relation he ſtands in un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:37402:30"/>to God Almighty himſelf, whoſe Image and Offspring he, in ſome ſenſe, is, this lets him ſee that he is under the ſtrongeſt Obligations in the World, of Duty, Reaſon and Honour, to do thoſe things which are Vertuous and Becoming, and to avoid the contrary. And, whereas, by this Contemplation of the human Nature, and of the Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers and Endowments which it hath pleaſed God to beſtow on it, he is made ſenſible that Vertue is a thing practicable and within his Power: This arms him againſt the ſugge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtions of thoſe who would diſcour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age him from attempting the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecution of Vertue and Felicity, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der pretence that they are things placed out of his reach: And on the other ſide, engages him to exert his utmoſt endeavours to attain as great a Perfection in Vertue as he can; ſince he ſees no reaſon to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpair of an Improvement corre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſponding to his Endeavours. He is
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:37402:30"/>perſuaded it is in his power to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come Vertuous and Happy; and that if he be not ſuch, 'twill be his own Fault. This excites his Reſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution and animates his Endeavours, and makes him with Courage and in good Earneſt ſet about that ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duous Affair, in which he has ſo good aſſurance of an anſwerable Succeſs. Thus Generoſity helps Men to eſtimate themſelves and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers rightly, and inſpires them with ſuch Sentiments and Reſoluti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, as ſerve both to diſpoſe them to Vertue, and likewiſe to render them vigorous in their endeavours to improve in that Character.</p>
            <p>Now if any Man ſhould at firſt be apt to think, that Generoſity leads Men to Pride, he may, I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve, without much difficulty, ſee that there is no ſuch matter, if he will but conſider well what Pride is. Now Pride, taken abſolutely or with reſpect to a Man's own ſelf, conſiſts in an unjuſt or exceſſive
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:37402:31"/>Opinion or Eſteem of one's ſelf. Unjuſt, when a Man either values himſelf for ſomething that he real<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly has not; which is the worſt ſort of Pride, and the moſt groſs and unreaſonable: Or elſe for ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, which properly ſpeaking, has not in it ſelf any real Worth, and ſo cannot communicate any to its poſſeſſor. Exceſſive, when he values himſelf more than he ought, for ſomething laudable, which he has really in ſome meaſure in him. But the Generous Man does not do either of theſe. It is his Chara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cter, that he values himſelf juſt ſo much as he ought; neither more nor leſs than he lawfully and fairly may. Now it is repugnant for a Man to value himſelf juſtly or exactly, and at the ſame time to value himſelf wrongfully or exceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſively. That is to be Proud, and not to be Proud, both at once. On the contrary, if we look exactly in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the thing, we may diſcern, that
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:37402:31"/>Generoſity produces the true and regular Humility, and ſuch a one as is perhaps both leſs artificial, and better grounded than any other. Thus Generous People are com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly found by experience, more addicted to Humility and Modeſty, and the Ungenerous to Pride and Inſolence. So alſo Pride, taken relatively, or with reſpect to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, is an unjuſt preferring our ſelves before other Men; when we falſly think we excel other Men. But the Generous Man is perhaps leſs inclined than others, to prefer himſelf. If he has an aſteem for himſelf, he has ſo likewiſe, and that upon the ſame Reaſons, for the Human Nature in general. If he eſteems himſelf for the Reſolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions he makes to uſe his Natural Freedom rightly, he eſteems other Men equally upon that account. And if another Man be more pun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctual in keeping his Reſolutions of that kind than himſelf is, he finds
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:37402:32"/>no difficulty to give him the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference. But in regard he does not eſteem himſelf for any thing which is not common to other Men equal<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly with himſelf; he is the leſs liable to be proud: Since Pride is ground<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed upon a conceit, that we have in us ſomething Excellent, which is not to be found in the generality of other Men. Men are not wont to be Proud, (I might ſay, cannot be ſo) for their having ſomewhat which every body elſe both has as well as they, and may, if he will, uſe as well as they do. One may be Proud, becauſe he either ſurpaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes other Men in Underſtanding, Strength, Beauty, or the like; or imagins that he doth ſo: But I ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver heard of any Body in his Sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes that was Proud, becauſe Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind at large, are rational and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>telligent Creatures, or becauſe they are of a comely and beautiful Fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gure, or upon the account of thoſe Qualities which are common to the
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:37402:32"/>whole Species. If Pride be a kind of Self-eſteem (as doubtleſs it is) it cannot take place in theſe Caſes, which do not relate to our ſelves only, but to Mankind in general. And to do right to thegenerous Man I muſt obſerve, that he does not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire to compare himſelf with thoſe who may perhaps come ſhort of him, in order to prefer himſelf before them, or gain a reputation from their Defects. But he rather chuſes to compare himſelf with thoſe who excel him, to the end he may be thereby excited to an emulation of their Vertue, and to a deſire of equalling or exceeding them if he can, in that which is Vertuous and Praiſe-worthy. In a word, if the generous Man endeavours to value both the Human Nature in gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral, and himſelf in particular, juſt ſo much as he lawfully may, and no more, then he cannot reaſonably be thought more, but indeed much leſs liable to Pride than other Men.</p>
            <pb n="52" facs="tcp:37402:33"/>
            <p>They indeed who are deſirous to faſten upon the Generous Man the imputation of Pride, upon any Terms, may perhaps carry the Charge a little further, and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend, that if he be not Proud with reſpect to Men, by preferring him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf unjuſtly before them, yet he is Proud and Aſſuming with reſpect to God Almighty, by arrogating to himſelf ſuch a freedom of Acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and ſuch a Power of chuſing and doing Good, as they imagine does detract from the divine Grace and Concurrence. But I deſire it may be conſidered, that the Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous Man does not aſſume to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf this natural Freedom and Choice, in oppoſition to the divine influence and concurrence, but in oppoſition to a neceſſity of acting. There is no Man more willing than he, to acknowledge, both the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendance which Mankind have on the divine Being; and likewiſe, that whatever Powers or good
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:37402:33"/>Qualifications they have, they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive the ſame from God Almighty, from whom, as the Scripture teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fies, and all conſidering Men ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge, even upon the foot of natural Theology, <q rend="inline">Every good Gift cometh.</q> But as he is ſatisfied, that both the Beginnings and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſes of Vertue and Goodneſs in Men, are from God Almighty: So he is alſo ſatisfied, from his own and the experience of all other Men, that Mankind are free Agents, and are obliged by the Laws of God and Man, to uſe that Freedom rightly. And therefore he does not think himſelf much concerned to determine (as ſome Men venture to do) in what particular manner God is pleaſed to communicate Vertues and good Qualities unto Men; or how, in particular, the divine Aids work with or upon that natural Freedom which we have, either antecedently or concomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tantly, or any, or what other way;
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:37402:34"/>or how in particular the Divine Concurrence and our natural Free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom conſiſt together. He thinks theſe are things, in a great meaſure out of his reach: And that as he can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not expect to acquire an entire Cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainty about them; ſo he may be as good a Man without the certain knowledge of them, as with it. But being on the own hand aſſured, that God Almighty is the primary Author of all good, he thinks, Men are obliged to depend on the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Majeſty, and to aſcribe to him the Beginnings and Increaſes of Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue and Goodneſs in them: And being on the other hand aſſured, that Mankind are free Agents, he ſees no reaſon to doubt, but that they can and ought to uſe that Freedom rightly, and that that is the way for them to become Vertuous and good Men.</p>
            <p>To this I may add, that the cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent Notions which Men have in caſes of this Nature about Self-e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteem;
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:37402:34"/>and about Pride and Humi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity, agree very well with what I have before ſpoken touching the Sentiments which accompany Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neroſity. We are not wont to blame Men, or account them Proud (nor can we indeed juſtly ſo do) for reſolving (which in the mean time ſuppoſes Freedom and Choice) to become as Vertuous and Good as they poſſibly can; or for believing, that their Reſolution and Endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour to be ſuch, is a proper and conducive means to that end: For thinking it beneath them, to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venge an Affront or Injury; or to commit a vile and ignominious thing: For having an ambition for that which is Vertuous, Decent and Venerable, and an abhorrence of the contrary, or the like. Theſe we eſteem laudable Principles and according to Vertue. And are wont to make uſe of the innate em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mulation and deſire of Glory, which we find in our ſelves or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers,
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:37402:35"/>in order to excite our ſelves or them to things of a worthy and becoming Nature. And on the other ſide, we cannot reaſonably, and, I think, uſually do not, eſteem it a Part or Inſtance of true Humi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity, for Men to diſparage and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grade the human Nature without grounds: Torepreſent Mankind as a company of neceſſary Agents, or of Beings either not at all Superiour to Brutes, or (which will render them much worſe than Brutes) void of all Goodneſs. Humility does not require that which is againſt Juſtice or Truth. So alſo we do not count it an inſtance of true Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mility, that a Man can deſcend to the vileſt Actions, and thinks no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing unbecoming or beneath him. But we rather, and no doubt very deſervedly, eſteem him to be in a profligate State, who has no regard to his Reputation or Honour.</p>
            <p>But further, as to thoſe Vertues or good Diſpoſitions of the Mind
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:37402:35"/>which belong to Generoſity, and by the Method before propoſed, come to be conſider'd next: I ſhall touch upon ſome of them now, and ſhall by and by have occaſion to ſpeak of ſome others, when I come to give a further Interpretation of this Principle, by ſhewing the Affi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity and Connexion there is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween it and ſeveral other Vertues of conſiderable Note. Now Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roſity does in general draw to it all thoſe Vertues which beſpeak a Manly temper of Mind, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce a tenour of Action becoming the human Nature; which Vertues I ſhall not go about exactly to enu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merate: But there are ſome which I muſt not omit naming particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larly, becauſe they ſeem to have a nearer cognation to it than ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary. Of this ſort are, Firmneſs of Mind, Goodneſs and Ingenuity of Temper, Liberality in diſtribu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting Favours, Sincerity and Recti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude of Spirit, Diſpaſſionateneſs or
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:37402:36"/>Tranquility, Evenneſs of Temper and Judgment, exact Obſervation of Decorum; in a word, an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tream Love and Veneration for Vertue.</p>
            <p>Wherein this Firmneſs of Mind principally conſiſts, may perhaps be moſt commodiouſly ſeen by con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidering the Qualities oppoſite to it. Now Firmneſs of Mind is op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed to that impotency of Spirit which lays Men open to the <hi>incurſions</hi> of Fear and Affrightment; by which their Reaſon is ſometimes rendred uſeleſs to them, and the Men ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jected to the Torment, Perplexi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, and other innumerable ill ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects of that extravagant Paſſion. It is oppoſed to that ſoftneſs or vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious Modeſty, which enclines Men to comply with others in things evil and diſhonourable (ſometimes even againſt their own Judgment) only to avoid their Confrontments or Reproaches. It is alſo oppoſed to another kind of impotency of Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit,
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:37402:36"/>whereby a Man for want of Judgment and of Reſolution to uſe his natural Freedom rightly, is either held from acting, by conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nual fluctuation of Mind, or can never keep a conſiſtency with him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf in the courſe of his Actions, but is oftentimes enclined to do and actually does thoſe things, of which he knows at the ſame time he ſhall afterwards have cauſe to Repent. It is alſo oppoſed to that ſort of im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>potency of Spirit, which keeps Men ſervilely under the power of Cuſtom and Prepoſſeſſion; and ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders them unable to quit thoſe Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rors which are fixt in them by Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtom, Education, or the power of fancy and corporeal Impreſſion, though upon the cleareſt Reaſons and fulleſt Conviction that can be. There are ſome People, who are very unhappy in this particular. They are oftentimes guided by Fan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy and Humour; by the cogitati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons which are raiſed in them by
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:37402:37"/>their Paſſions or corporeal Impreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions, which though never ſo ſlight and trivial, they have accuſtomed themſelves to attend unto; not conſidering ſo much, whether they have any ſolid reaſon for what they do reſolve to do, as whether their Humour, Fancy or Prepoſſeſſion encline them to do it: And not di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinguiſhing the Impreſſions that are made upon them by external things, or by their own Imagination, and the Perceptions which are by theſe means excited in their Brain and Spirits, from the Principles of the rational Nature, or the Cogitati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons that purely relate to the Soul, ſuffer themſelves to be carried away by uncertain and fortuitous Impreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions, in ſo much that they act as it were by chance, without being able in many things, to give a tole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable reaſon for what they do. This habit betokens a great Infirmity: And as it is moſt incident to Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men and People of effeminate and
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:37402:37"/>feeble Spirits, ſo it is directly op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſite to Generoſity. It is oppoſed alſo, to another kind of Impoten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy of Spirit, whereby Men are un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to demean themſelves ſteadily and evenly in the two different ſtates of Life: But are either tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſported to an exceſs of Levity and Folly by Proſperity, or confound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and diſpirited by the acceſs of Adverſity. It is alſo oppoſed to that ſort of Impotency of Spirit, which diſcovers it ſelf by Trepi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dity upon the approach of Danger, by a dulneſs and drowſineſs of Mind, and by an averſion to undertake or go through thoſe Poſts and Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployments which are attended with labour and hazard. Theſe and ſuch like are the Qualities oppoſite to it. So that if we turn the Tables, we ſhall eaſily ſee wherein this firmneſs of Mind conſiſts: To wit, in Cour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age and Conſtancy, in a judicious Uniformity of acting, in the preſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence of Reaſon over our Prejudi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:37402:38"/>and corporeal Impreſſions, in a conſtancy and evenneſs under every State of Life, in a diſcreet bold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and activity. And ſince theſe Qualities which I have mentioned as oppoſite to firmneſs of Mind, diſcover an imbecillity of Spirit, and diſpoſe Men to act upon child<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſh and weak Principles; the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary Qualities may, not impro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perly, be thought to belong to the Character of Generoſity.</p>
            <p>The goodneſs and ingenuouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of Temper which I juſt now mentioned, conſiſts in that Candor and Humanity which renders Men peaceable, agreeable and well hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moured, willing to paſs by Injuries upon reaſonable Terms, and to put the moſt favourable conſtruction that may fairly be upon things; which fills Men with ſentiments of Tenderneſs and Compaſſion, and of Clemency and Mercy; which makes them obliging and civil in Converſation; and enclines them
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:37402:38"/>to render not only unto their Friends and Neighbours, but like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe to Strangers and others, as occaſion may be, the reſpective of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fices of Curteſy and Good-will, and to do all that lies in their power to preſerve and maintain amity and good underſtanding with thoſe with whom they converſe. For the Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerous Man has an eſteem for the human Nature in general; and therefore thinks, that all Men are entituled to thoſe reſpects and good Offices which identity of Blood and Nature challenge from him. He remembers likewiſe the imbecil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lities that belong to human Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture; that no Man is wiſe at all times; that there are a great ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny accidents and emerging Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances which lead Men inſenſibly into Error, inſomuch that the moſt vigilant and cautious are ſometime or other deceived and intrapped: And therefore he is not apt to be ſevere in his Cenſures, or to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demn
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:37402:39"/>Men of improbity or inſince<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity for a ſingle unadviſed Action. The knowledge he has of his own Infirmity, reſtrains him in that particular, and makes him willing to give other Mens Actions that connivance or favourable Conſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction which he himſelf may deſire or ſtand in need of for his own. And when he conſiders, that other Men, as well as himſelf, have by Nature the free diſpoſal of their own Wills, he is diſpoſed to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve, that they reſolve as well as himſelf does, to uſe that power rightly, and thereupon that the Errors or Faults which they com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit, are owing rather to want of Judgment or to Incogitancy, than to ill Will or ſiniſter Intention. And when he obſerves on the one hand, how much the ſeveral ſocial Vertues contribute to make Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſation agreeable, delightful and orderly; and on the other hand, how much the contrary Qualities
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:37402:39"/>contribute to diſturb and bring it into diſorder: He thinks himſelf obliged by theſe Conſiderations, and likewiſe by the Rules of Good-breeding and Decorum, to endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour to exerciſe thoſe Vertues which are of ſo great Uſe and Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nament.</p>
            <p>Liberality in diſtributing Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours, is another Qualification be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longing to Generoſity. This is ſo far acknowledged by moſt Men, that in ordinary Diſcourſe, the li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beral Man is moſt uſually honoured with the name of Generous. But tho' Liberality does not give us a compleat Idea of Generoſity; for Generoſity is not to be reſtrained within ſo narrow a compaſs: Yet it is true, that this is one of its Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racters. Now this Liberality is, in a Generous Man, attended with ſuch Sentiments as theſe: An E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteem for Mankind on general, which makes him look in them as proper Objects, not only of Juſtice,
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:37402:40"/>but alſo of Kindneſs and Benefi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cence; a ſerenity of Mind mixt with the Perceptions of Kindneſs and Gratitude, and a ſenſe of De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corum; which kind of Sentiments ſerve to open his Heart, and to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe him as well to make ſuitable acknowledgments of Favours and Obligations, as likewiſe to do theſe and other things in ſuch a manner as may ſeem moſt becoming a great Mind.</p>
            <p>To Generoſity do likewiſe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long Sincerity and Rectitude of Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit: Of which I ſhall have occaſion to ſpeak more particularly anon.</p>
            <p>And to it likewiſe belong Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſionateneſs and Tranquility. 'Tis well known, that Mens Paſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and unbridled Appetites do ruffle and diſorder them to a ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry great degree, and by diſturbing the regular uſe of their natural Freedom, and raiſing Storms and Tempeſts in their Minds, impel them to the commiſſion of many
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:37402:40"/>fooliſh, extravagant and wicked things, which afterwards bring upon them ſhame, regret, remorſe of Conſcience, and many other In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conveniences. Now Generoſity is adapted to remedy theſe Evils. For the Generous Man, by the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand he has over his own Spirit, and the Government he maintains over his Paſſions and Inclinations, is the better ſecured in that Tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quility, which the regular uſe of Mens natural Freedom is wont to produce: And ſince he endeavours to do nothing whereof he ſhall have juſt cauſe afterwards to Repent, he is the more likely to eſcape Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morſe of Conſcience; than which there is nothing that gives the Mind a more ſharp and tormenting Pain.</p>
            <p>Evenneſs of Temper in Judging and Acting is another Property of Generoſity. This is much the ſame with that which is ſometimes called in one word Moderation.
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:37402:41"/>And is produced or maintained by that Firmneſs of Mind and Tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quility, which I have before men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned. It is eaſy to diſcern, that the due government of a Man's Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, and of his Paſſions, corporeal Impreſſions and Inclinations, the irregularities whereof do ſo much pervert Mens Judgments concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing things, and betray them into ſo many weak and wicked Actions, muſt needs conduce very much to eſtabliſh him in this even Temper of Mind.</p>
            <p>Exact obſervation of Decorum, is likewiſe another Property of Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neroſity. We know there are ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral things, either Lawful or at leaſt countenanced by the general Practice of Men, which yet are real<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly not expedient or fitting to be done; as being againſt Decency and good Grace. In ſuch Caſes, the Generous Man conſiders, not barely what is lawful or practica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, but withal what is decent and
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:37402:41"/>ſeemly. The reſpect he has for the Humane Nature, enclines him to conceal its imperfections; to cover what is uncomely with the vail of Modeſty; and to ſubmit quietly to the laws of the animal nature without violating Puri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty or Decency internally in his Mind, or openly in his words or actions. He will not offer un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>handſome things to Matrons or Virgins, or put modeſt perſons to the bluſh; and endeavours in gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral, to avoid ſuch words and geſtures as are ungraceful. So likewiſe he is not apt to be aſſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, impertinent, or troubleſome in company; to put the banter and ridicule upon others; to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flect upon them or inſult over their weakneſs and imperfection; to pry into other Mens ſecrets, or meddle with matters which do not concern him. He bears with ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny things, connives at, and paſſes many things over in ſilence. In
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:37402:42"/>a word, he conſiders his ſex, his age, his ſtation, his character, and the circumſtances of his condition, and endeavours with reſpect to them all, to comport himſelf as neer as he can by the rules of Decorum. And ſince Decency is a thing of a refined and delicate nature, and the perfection as it were of Right and Lawful, as Equity is the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection of Juſtice: The Generous Man, who reſolves to do, to his power, that which is beſt and moſt becoming, and to attain as high a degree in Vertue as he can, muſt neeeds find himſelf under an obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation to obſerve the rules of De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cency.</p>
            <p>In ſhort, Generoſity imports an extreme Love and Veneration for Vertue. The Generous Man looks upon Vertue and Goodneſs to be the moſt honourable and becoming thing in the World, and the greateſt Ornament and perfection of the Human nature. It is to
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:37402:42"/>him the great index and rule of Honourable and Diſhonourable. And therefore when he looks round about him, he can ſee nothing that deſerves to be the object of his eſteem and ambition in compariſon of it: Being ſatisfied, that there is nothing ſo worthy of his care and regard, as that which tends to advance him to a conformity unto the ſupreme and moſt perfect Being, and which leads him in a direct line to the trueſt and high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt Felicity his nature is capable of. So that when he reſolves to uſe his natural Freedom rightly, and to proſecute with all his might that which is ſimply and abſolute<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly beſt; he does ſo, for the ſake of Vertue; That is the ſecret Spring of his motions, and the Butt of his Ambition.</p>
            <p>This may ſerve for a general ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plication of the nature of Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roſity. In the next place I am to ſpeak ſomewhat, to ſhew the a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greement
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:37402:43"/>and affinity there is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween it, and ſeveral other Vertues which have been deſervedly eſteem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed of the firſt rank; and likewiſe between it, and ſome of thoſe ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent rules of conduct which have been approved by the common con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent of mankind in moſt ages of the World. And after that, I would conſider briefly the influence it has even upon what is more ſtrictly called Piety and Religion. By all which it may appear, that the ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timents and diſpoſitions of mind which Generoſity is attended with all, do entirely correſpond and are in effect the ſame with thoſe ſentiments and diſpoſitions which the moſt eminent Vertues and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proved rules of Action ſerve to produce in us. And the doing of this will, I conceive, not only af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford us a fuller interpretation of the Principle which we are now conſidering, but likewiſe be of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderable uſe to us in our Practice.</p>
            <pb n="73" facs="tcp:37402:43"/>
            <p>Now there are ſix Principal Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues, which I ſhall take particular notice of in this place; to wit, Prudence, Sincerity, and Patience; which are called Primitive Vertues: And Juſtice, Fortitude, and Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perance, which are called Deriva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive ones.</p>
            <p>Prudence is a Vertue, whereby a Man judges rightly of things. And this no Man can well do, who is not competently free from the power of Prejudice, Paſſion, and the other imbecillities which hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der Men from the clear diſcern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of what is good and true. Now it is the generous Mans con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant endeavour to overcome, and keep his Mind free from thoſe im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pediments; as I have before no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted: And by that means he is very much ſecured from ſeveral of thoſe errors which are oppoſite to Pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, ſuch as Raſhneſs, Precipi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, Levity, Credulity, Obſtina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, blind Zeal, Partiality, and
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:37402:44"/>the like: And on the contrary is diſpoſed and enabled to judg and chuſe rightly. To explain this, I ſhall at preſent only make uſe of the following inſtance, waiving others which might be given. We find, there is a ſort of Imprudence which Men are betrayed into by an unaccountable gayety of temper that ſometimes befalls them. And though this be commonly moſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cident to young People, who by reaſon of the fire and briskneſs that is in their Blood and Spirits, are moſt apt to be carried away by vehement and ſudden emotions; yet there are many who retain this levity and gayety of temper, till they come to be far advanced in years. Now Generoſity helps to correct the Irregularities of this temper; as it ballaſts and poiſes the Mind, and excites Men to do thoſe things only, which are grave, manly, and diſcreet; that is, to act according to the rules of Pru<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dence.
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:37402:44"/>And in regard 'tis part of the character of a Generous Man, firmly and adviſedly to reſolve to proſecute, in all his actions as neer as he can, that which is ultimately and ſimply beſt: Whilſt we ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe him to do that, we muſt ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe him to be competently conu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant and capable of judging what is beſt: that is, to be at leaſt a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petently Prudent Man.</p>
            <p>Sincerity is a Vertue, whereby a Man is diſpoſed, ſincerely and uprightly to proſecute that which he deems to be ſimply beſt. This Vertue is one of the brighteſt cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racters of the Soul: 'Tis the life and Spirit of other Vertues; And that which is in a particular man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner pleaſing and acceptable to God Almighty, as we may judg from the nature of the thing, and as ſufficiently appears from ſeveral expreſs Declarations in the Goſpel of our Saviour. So that 'twill be a great Recommendation to Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roſity,
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:37402:45"/>if that be found to have a Cognation with it. Now Sinceri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty has an eſpecial relation to the Will. It conſiſts in a ſimplicity of Mind, and a Rectitude of Will and intention. It is that Purity and uncorrupt Chaſtity of the Will, whereby a Man is engaged to ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>here unto that which appears to be beſt. But Generoſity is like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe accompanied with the ſame diſpoſition of Mind, which Sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerity produces in Men. For Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neroſity has in like manner an eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecial relation to the Will. It is attended with that Rectitude of the Will, whereby a Man is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinually engaged to endeavour to uſe his Natural Freedom rightly, and to chuſe and do, to his power, in all caſes, that which appears to be beſt. The very deſcription of theſe two correſpond mutually, and enter into one another. Since that which appears to be beſt, is for an inviolable Law both to the
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:37402:45"/>ſincere, and to the Generous Man; theſe two Vertues muſt needs have the ſtricteſt Connexion imagina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble.</p>
            <p>As for Patience, which is a Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue of the Soul, whereby a Man for the ſake of Vertue and Good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs is contented to endure thoſe things which are difficult and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ungrateful to the Animal nature: This Vertue evidently appertains to Generoſity; and may in parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tular be referred to the Maſculine Firmneſs of Mind, which makes part of that character. For Pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence do's not reſide in a feeble Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit; or in a Breaſt agitated with untamed and impetuous Paſſions. It dwells in Maſculine and firm Minds; which are able to endure the ſhock of Hardſhips; and think it inglorious to ſhrink when they are engaged in the Cauſe of Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue. Thus alſo the Generous Man confirms himſelf in a reſolution to bear the injuries of Men and other
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:37402:46"/>misfortunes that may befall him; And though he does not throw himſelf raſhly into dangers or mis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortunes; yet he reſolves to go through them with an even and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daunted Spirit. Nor indeed can the Generous Man, without a due Proportion of the Maſculine Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue of Patience, execute thoſe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolutions which he makes of pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuing the higheſt good. Without it, the formidable proſpect of Death, Pain, Poverty, Shame, on the like, would quickly break his Meaſures, and diſſolve his Reſolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions. And therefore he thinks he is obliged to arm himſelf with this Vertue, that he may be able the more conſtantly and ſteadily to put in are the juſt Reſolutions he makes of acting upon the Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples of Honour and Vertue. So likewiſe we may obſerve, that there are a great many things which put Men into diſorder and impati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, that do befall them unavoid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ably
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:37402:46"/>and without their own choice; ſuch as neither their In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duſtry or Foreſight can prevent: And that on the other Hand, Men do oftentimes, by their own folly and peeviſhneſs, create Vexati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons to themſelves, when it is in their power to be in quiet. And whether Men are under misfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunes of the Firſt or Latter ſort, we find by experience, that the greateſt part of the uneaſineſs they endure in thoſe caſes, is owing to the impatience and ungovernable<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of their Spirits, by means whereof that which would other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe be eaſy to be endured, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comes intolerable to them. Now as to the vexations which we vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luntarily bring upon our ſelves, I need not ſay that Generoſity helps us to endure them, for (which is much better) it does really help to prevent them. It tends to cure Men of thoſe little freaks and imbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cillities of Spirit which are the
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:37402:47"/>cauſe of them: And ſo by taking away the cauſe, takes away the effect. And as to the other ſort of misfortunes which 'tis leſs in our power to prevent, Generoſity, which helps us to govern our Paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions and Appetites, which arms our Minds with Maſculine Reſolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, in a Word, which makes us ſenſible that there is all the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon in the World to ſubmit pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently to the ſoveraign and wiſe Government of Almighty God, whether he diſtribute ſweet or un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grateful things, and to ſuffer hardſhips for the ſake of Vertue: I ſay, Generoſity which operates within us in this manner, muſt needs conduce very much to beget in us a patience and conſtancy of Mind.</p>
            <p>Next conſider Juſtice, which is a conſtant and uniform purpoſe of giving to every one his due. Now the Generous Man purſues the dictates of this Vertue. And is
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:37402:47"/>willing to do right, both to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, and likewiſe to every body elſe. For he neither envies nor hates any body. He thinks it a diſhonourable part to do an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſt thing to another, either by detracting from his juſt deſert, or by wronging him in his Eſtate, his Bed, or his Perſon. And ſo he is kept from ſeveral Vices, which are oppoſite to Juſtice, ſuch as Slander, falſe Teſtimony and Subordination, Bribery and unjuſt Judgment, Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vetouſneſs, Extortion, Murder, Adultery, Rapine, Oppreſſion, fraud, Cruelty, and the like. Nay, he is not content to do ſtrict Juſtice to other Men; But chuſeth to render them more than what is in ſtrict<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs due, rather than leſs. He re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laxes and qualifies, as far as he lawfully may, what is rigorous and extreme; and exerciſeth Juſtice with that Moderation and Equity which is indeed the Flower and perfection of it. And ſince it is
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:37402:48"/>part of his character, that he has no mighty value for Honour, Riches, or the like external things, he is under the leſs temptation to wrong others in order to advance or enrich himſelf with their ſpoils. So likewiſe he eſteems it a mean and abject thing, to be ungrateful to ſuch as have obliged him or done him good offices: And therefore is careful to ſhew, upon all fit oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſions, his gratitude to his Bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>factors; accounting it a piece of Juſtice and Honour ſo to do. And he is likewiſe careful to demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate an entire Fidelity to thoſe who have committed to him a Truſt; accounting it both unjuſt and mean-ſpirited, to be treache<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous or unfaithful. And whilſt he conſiders the ſtrait alliance and conſanguinity there is between Man and Man, upon account of the common nature they are all partakers of; and likewiſe the juſt Title that all Men who are not fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>len
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:37402:48"/>from the common Rights of their nature, have, not only to his eſteem and good will, but alſo to all thoſe good offices which 'tis in his power upon reaſonable terms to render to them: He finds himſelf engaged, even in point of Juſtice, to be courteous, affable, eaſy of acceſs, humane, candid, and obliging to all Men; and to exerciſe, as far as he fairly may, the reſpective offices of Charity, Beneficence, Hoſpitality, and Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lanthropy, towards them. And as he thinks himſelf obliged to do thoſe things which Juſtice requires with reſpect to mankind: So he conſiders alſo the Juſtice that is due to Almighty God: And this en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gages him to the exact performance of the reſpective Offices of Piety which relate to Almighty God. So likewiſe he remembers, that he ows a duty and Reſpect to Truth alſo. And this obliges him to an entire Veracity; and makes him
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:37402:49"/>punctual to his promiſes and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tracts, as far as lies really and <hi>bona fide</hi> in his power. And conſider<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, that Lying, Equivocating, or Diſſembling, are mean and raſcally actions, and for the moſt part the tokens of an abject Spirit; he finds himſelf obliged to avoid theſe and ſuch like little Arts, if he would purſue the Character of a Juſt and Generous Man.</p>
            <p>As for Fortitude, whereby Men are enabled, for the ſake of Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue and Goodneſs, to atchieve and undergo great and difficult things, and even to ſuffer Death it ſelf with a firm and intrepid Mind: It is ſo neerly allied to Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neroſity, that ſeveral of the Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racters of Generoſity have been wont to be aſcribed by Moraliſts to it; and to be repreſented under the name of Fortitude or Magna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nimity. Now Fortitude or Mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nanimity conſiſting in that true Gallantry of Mind which qualifies
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:37402:49"/>Men for great undertakings, which enables them to encounter with a conſtant and ſerene mind, the dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficulties and dangers that attend elevated imployments both in Peace and War; and all this, in gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral for the ſake of Honeſty and Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue, and in particular for the good and ſafety of their Country: Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neroſity and It appear to have an undivided cognation. And as For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude has in moſt ages been eſteem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and honoured in a peculiar man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner; inſomuch that the other good habits or powers of the Soul are called Vertues from the proper name of this: So the Generous Man has a Genius peculiarly ſuited to make good the characters of that Vertue. And though he be as ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible of Pain and misfortunes as other Men, yet he endeavours to keep his Spirit from being oppreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed or ſoftned by them; and in a word, to ſupport himſelf under all, with a ſteadineſs and conſtancy be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coming his character.</p>
            <pb n="86" facs="tcp:37402:50"/>
            <p>Then for Temperance, which is a Vertue, whereby Men are re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrained in the uſe of ſenſitive plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures, that they may the better purſue things more ſublime and noble: This is evidently of kin to Generoſity; which likewiſe ſug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſts, that we ought to poſtpone all manner of ſenſitive Gratificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons to thoſe other exerciſes of the Mind whereby it is led to that which is ſimply and abſolutely beſt. He cannot proſecute that which is abſolutely beſt, with a juſt Vigour, who is continually enclined to gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tify the Body in its ſeveral Appe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tites; becauſe there is nothing that does, more than that, hinder Men in the purſuit of Vertue and Goodneſs. But the Generous Man is ſenſible, that 'tis unbecoming the dignity of the Rational nature; for a Man to indulge himſelf too much in corporeal pleaſures, or gratify the extravagant deſires of the Body: That this would be to
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:37402:50"/>ſet the Rational and the Animal na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture upon the ſame Level, or per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps to prefer the Latter before the Former: And being ſatisfied, it is no part of true Humility, to condeſcend ſo low, he endeavours to maintain the dignity of that rank and order, wherein God Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty hath placed him. And all this he does, not out of a Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt of other Creatures more ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noble than himſelf, but out of a juſt eſteem of the Dignity of his own Order, and out of a ſincere regard to Vertue. And when he obſerves, how much, Voluptuouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs tends to bewitch Mens Minds, to render Men ſoft, terrene, and degenerate, and to extinguiſh the Seeds of goodneſs in them: He concludes, that if he be not tempe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate and diſcreet in the uſe of ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſual pleaſures, he ſhall be in appa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent danger of forfeiting thoſe Vertuous habits and diſpoſitions of Mind, wherein he places his
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:37402:51"/>greateſt Honour and Happineſs. And thus he is armed againſt ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Vices that are oppoſite to Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perance, ſuch as Laſciviouſneſs, Exceſs in Meats and Drinks, Va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity in Behaviour or Apparel, and other ſoftneſses wherein there is any thing of Luxury or Abuſe.</p>
            <p>But further, as touching thoſe excellent Rules of conduct, which I before took notice of, let us ſee how Generoſity ſtands with re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect to them. Of this ſort there are two principally to be conſider<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed. <q rend="inline">Do as you would be done by:</q> And, <q rend="inline">Know thy ſelf.</q>
            </p>
            <p>As for the former of theſe, <q rend="inline">Do unto others as you would they ſhould do unto you; and, Do not to others what you would not they ſhould do unto you:</q> They are ſo eaſy to be underſtood and applied, that I need ſay no more of them, than that they contain the Sum of Natural Juſtice and E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity; and being of a comprehen
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:37402:51"/>five and delicate nature, do not only direct us to act according to the Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary Rules of Juſtice, but like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe ſerve to guide us by the Rules of Equity and Mercy, where thoſe of Juſtice ſeem to be either ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcure or defective. And this is one great uſe of Generoſity, which is alſo a Principle ſo comprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſive, that as I have already ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved, it imports in it the Sum of that Juſtice and Equity which Men ow to one another, and is of ſo fine and delicate a nature, that it reſtrains Men from doing many things, which according to human Laws or the ordinary Rules of Juſtice, may appear lawful, and enclines them oftentimes, as the circumſtances of things may be, to do more than thoſe ordinary Rules in ſtrictneſs require at their hands.</p>
            <p>As to the latter Precept, <q rend="inline">Know thy Self.</q> This we are told was formerly had in great Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence,
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:37402:52"/>inſomuch that 'twas ſuppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to have been immediately com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municated unto Men from Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven—<hi>E Coelo deſcendit,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. And it well deſerves to be eſteem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and obſerved at this day. Now the Knowledge of our ſelves is of uſe principally two ways: To wit. As it makes us ſenſible on the one hand of the Imperfections, and on the other of the Dignity of our Nature. Firſt, by Knowing our Selves, and by contemplating the Infirmities and Imperfections that adhere to our Nature, we are taught to be humble and modeſt, patient, temperate, ſubmiſſive to the divine Will, beneficent and merciful, and the like. When we we conſider, that our Knowledge and other Abilities are compara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tively imperfect, how many things we are ignorant of, and in how many we err and do amiſs: This and ſuch like Conſiderations help to keep us from being Proud and
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:37402:52"/>Preſuming with reſpect to our ſelves, and from being rigid, cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſorious and ill-natured, with re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect to others whom we find of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fending or miſtaken. And, on the contrary, diſpoſe us to Charity, Goodneſs, Forbearance, Candor and Mercy towards them: Since we are thereby made ſenſible, that we our ſelves are liable to many, or all, of the Errors and Offences which we ſee in other Men. So likewiſe when we obſerve, how helpleſs and impotent we are, how unable to forſee or prevent the ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cidents, revolutions and changes that attend our Lives, and either to procure to our ſelves many of thoſe external good Things which we want, or to avert thoſe Miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortunes which we ſuffer or appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hend, it ſuggeſts to us a notable Leſſon of Patience and of Submiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to Almighty God, as the moſt effectual means to keep a ſerenity in our Minds, notwithſtanding all
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:37402:53"/>that may befal us. And further, when we conſider the frailty and abjectneſs of our Bodies, that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the meaneſt and moſt deſpica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble part of us, they do not deſerve we ſhould be ſo very intent upon the gratifying of them, much leſs that our Solicitude about them ſhould either exceed or hinder our care and concern about our nobler and better Part: This inſtructs us to avoid Covetouſneſs, Intempe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance and Exceſs in the Love or Uſe of things relating to the Body. And, further, when under the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration of this Infirmity of our preſent State, we become ſenſible, that there are many things neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry to the ſupport and well being of Men, and that therefore ſuch as are deſtitute of theſe things, deſerve to be conſider'd by us, as far as we are fairly able; that is an Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to us, to give them help and and relief: Eſpecially when we remember, that by reaſon of the
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:37402:53"/>mutability of our condition in this World, we our ſelves, tho' per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps at preſent in a flouriſhing State, may be an eaſy turn of Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fairs, be brought into the ſame ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſitous condition we ſee others in.</p>
            <p>But then the Knowledge of our ſelves is likewiſe of uſe another way, <hi>viz.</hi> as it makes us ſenſible of the Dignity of our Nature; and by that means engages us to the doing of ſuch things as are becom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Character we bear in the Creation, and deters us from do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing whatever is diſparaging or diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>agreeable to that Character. For ſince Vertue is in its Nature Noble and Honourable; and Vice the quite contrary: Upon that Princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, the Knowledge of our Selves ſerves to excite in us on the one hand that laudable Ambition, whereby we aſpire after thoſe things which are Vertuous and truly Honourable, and on the other
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:37402:54"/>hand that commendable Shame which deters us from things of the contrary Nature. Now Generoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty operates both theſe ways. It confirms Men on the one hand in a juſt Humility, Meekneſs, Patience, Charity, and other like Vertues, as may appear from what has been already ſaid: And on the other hand, diſpoſes Men to thoſe Vertues which are produced and maintained by the conſideration of the Dignity of the human Nature, and of the Obligations that reſult from thence to act agreeably to that Character: But it is more pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culiarly ſuited to operate this latter way: As it excites in Men that no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Ambition, which is grounded on the conſideration of the honour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Nature of Vertue, and of the auſpicious and happy Conſequences it brings after it, and that vertu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Shame which is grounded on the turpitude and diſhonourable Nature of Vice, and of the miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chievous
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:37402:54"/>and unhappy Effects which attend it. For the Generous Man, according to that excellent Precept, <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <q rend="inline">Above all Revere thy Self</q>, would be ambitious of Vertue, tho' he had no proſpect of acquiring external Reputation by it, and would be touch'd with a ſenſe of Shame, if he went about to commit a vile Action never ſo privately, even where he could be in no danger of publick diſparagement. So that the Sentiments which are raiſed in Men by the juſt Knowledge of themſelves, agree with thoſe which are raiſed in them by the Principle of Generoſity: Both ſerving to ſpur them on to vertuous and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coming Actions, and to deter them from foul and vitious ones, from much the ſame Conſiderations.</p>
            <p>But Generoſity enters alſo into that part of Religion which more immediately relates to God Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty; and mixes it ſelf with
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:37402:55"/>the habits of Piety and Devotion. There are three great faults, to wit, Superſtition, Hypocriſy, and Prophaneneſs, into one or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of which, thoſe who err with reſpect to Religion, commonly fall. And Generoſity is ſuited to help againſt each of theſe. Againſt Superſtition; as it excites in mens minds manly and becoming thoughts of Almighty God, ſuch as are ſuitable to the Divine Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture: By which means it ſerves to rid their Minds of thoſe light and childiſh conceptions touching the Nature and Worſhip of God, which are the Seeds of Bigottry and Superſtition. For when Men have by the Divine aid, and by due care and exerciſe, habituated their Minds to juſt apprehenſions of the Pure and Excellent Nature of God: They cannot think it ſufficient, to expreſs the veneration and ſervice which they ow unto him, by thoſe trivial and inſignificant inſtances
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:37402:55"/>of Devotion and Worſhip, or that partial and reſerved Obedience, which ſuperſtitious and weak Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple are wont to content them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves withal; or indeed by any thing leſs than an entire dedicati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of their Souls and Bodies to him, in pure and ardent Devotion, joyned with an entire and hearty Obedience to his Laws; that is, by adjuſting both their Worſhip and Converſation unto a confor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity to his moſt Excellent Nature And when likewiſe, they have poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſed their Minds with manly and Rational thoughts of Religion: they will be the leſs ſubject to be carried away by the errours of Enthuſiaſm and pretended Spiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuality; which is alſo a kind of Superſtition.</p>
            <p>And for Hypocriſy, which is another great Abuſe of Religion; Generoſity is naturally ſuited to cure or prevent it. For Genero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity is wont to be accompanied
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:37402:56"/>with ſuch a Sincerity of Mind, as is not conſiſtent with Hypocriſy. And whilſt it teaches Men to act upon the true Principles of Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, it will eaſily make them ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible; that 'tis an unworthy and baſe practice, to go about to delude other Men with a Pretence of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, when at the ſame time they are conſcious to themſelves, that they have nothing of that Princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple within them; and that Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion is a thing of ſo noble and ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vated a nature, that it ought not to be made ſubſervient to the little ends of Worldly profit and inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt.</p>
            <p>So alſo Generoſity helps againſt Prophaneneſs. For ſince Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roſity is founded in the juſt know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledg of our ſelves; from the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration, that we are compara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tively frail and impotent Creatures, and entirely dependant on God Almighty for our Being and all that we have; it ſerves to ſuppreſs in
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:37402:56"/>us thoſe extravagant and big thoughts of our ſelves, which would lead us to prophaneneſs and contempt of God; and on the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to engage us to love and gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude to his Divine Majeſty, from whom we continually receive ſo many demonſtrations of Bounty and Philanthropy. And from the conſideration of the infinite diſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance there is betwixt God and Men, it ſerves to awaken the innate Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciple we have in us, of honour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and reverencing whatever per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon or being appears to be Great and Excellent; and ſo engages us to expreſs that Honour and Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence we have for Almighty God (who is infinitely the greateſt and moſt excellent Being) in ſuch ways as are moſt proper to ſignify and declare the ſame; to wit, by Worſhip, Reverence of him, and all that relates to him, and by Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formity to his Nature and Laws, as far as we are able. Which
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:37402:57"/>is indeed the Sum of Religion.</p>
            <p>From theſe ſhort inſtances it may be ſeen, that Generoſity is a Principle neerly allied to the ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Vertues of the Divine Life, and likewiſe extremely accommo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dated to preſerve Men ſtraight and even in the practice of true Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. And theſe conſiderations will, I conceive, ſerve both to explain the Notion of Generoſity, and likewiſe to ſhew the intimate A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greement there is between Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and Honour, being rightly un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood and applied. So much then for what I propoſed to ſpeak in the Interpretation of Generoſity.</p>
            <p>But now I am well aware, that 'tis likely, that ſuch perſons as have been accuſtomed to frame a narrow and reſtrained notion of Genero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity, and to think it conſiſts only in Liberality, or what is common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly called good breeding, or ſuch like, may imagine, that I do amiſs, in taking it in ſo large and compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſive
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:37402:57"/>a ſenſe, and attributing to it ſuch noble Characters, as I have done. But I am perſuaded, that when things come to be weighed, I ſhall be acquitted of blame in that particular. I have been conſider<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Generoſity, not barely as a particular Vertue or good quality, but chiefly as ſuch a Principle in the Rational Soul as is of a Metaphyſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal and univerſal nature. Now the Principles of this kind are ſuch that they may be applied as vari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly as there are various actions in human life: And ſo muſt needs be of a large and comprehenſive na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, ſince they pervade the whole Body of a mans Cogitations and Actions, and are the Principles from which he Acts, not only in ſome few but in very many caſes. And that Generoſity is a Principle of this kind, may appear from what I have already ſaid. Even mens Natural Temper, diſcovers it ſelf in moſt of their actions, in
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:37402:58"/>Natural, Civil, Moral and Religious ones. And ſo far as it hath influence up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Mind, produces as great a vari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ety of ſenſations and diſpoſitions in the Man, as there is great variety of Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects about which he is converſant. But the Principles immediately referring to the Mind, are much more accommoda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to ſpread through all the actions of a Man: For as the Mind is the ſeat of a Mans Thoughts, and his Thoughts the Spring of his Actions: So the Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples of the Mind, which have the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of univerſal Cogitations, are as uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſal in their Operation, as they are in their Root; or if you will, as univer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſal conſidered objectively, as they are, conſidered formally. Thus Sincerity taken as a general Principle of the Mind, extends it ſelf to moſt of the actions of Ruman Life, to thoſe which fall under a Civil, Moral or Religious Conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: And may be exerted by Men of all Faculties, Profeſſions, Trades, Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders and Degrees, in the actions which relate to the ſeveral conditions of Life, by which they are diverſified from one another, and in thoſe which are com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon to them all. The ſame may be ſaid of the general Principle of Pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence:
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:37402:58"/>And likewiſe of the general Frinciple of Generoſity. And if Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roſity be ſuch a Principle, as is, not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly of a large and extended Nature, but is likewiſe in an extraordinary manner congenial and agreeable to the moſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fined Principles of our Minds, and is accompanied with, or ſerves to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce in us, thoſe ſentiments and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſitions of Mind, which tend to the advancement and perfection of our Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture: I ſay, if the Caſe be ſo, I am perſuaded, I cannot be juſtly accuſed of having extended the Notion of it too far, or having given it too high Characters.</p>
            <p>But I think I need not be very ſoli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citous about this Matter. 'Tis ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent for me, that however ſome Men may diſlike or quarrel with the Name of Generoſity, becauſe perhaps they have been uſed to ſpeak of thoſe things which make up its Character, in other Terms than thoſe I here uſe, or for o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Reaſons beſt known to themſelves: Yet they cannot, without doing ſome violence to their own Minds, but ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mire and eſteem the Thing, and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge that the Characters which I have ſaid do belong to it, import that
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:37402:59"/>which is really Noble and Illuſtrious. And peradventure, they may diſcern that Mankind do univerſally agree in theſe Sentiments, when they obſerve how naturally and readily Men are wont to deſcribe Perſons or Actions that are eminent for their goodneſs and rectitude, by the Name of Generous, Great, Noble, and ſuch like Epithets, which properly belong to this Chara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cter.</p>
            <p>If then the ancient Philoſophers and Moraliſts do not make mention of Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neroſity under that particular Name, or, deſcribe it with exactly the ſame Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racters which I have herein attributed to it, that ought not to be any Preju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dice againſt what I have ſaid upon this Head. We all ſpeak the ſame thing in ſubſtance and effect, and ſometimes in much the ſame words. What is Generoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty but an <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, a fortitude or manli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of Spirit, a <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, or great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of Soul? What is it but a <hi>Compoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum jus faſ<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> animi,</hi> a ſteady rectitude of the Mind, a <hi>Generoſum honeſtum,</hi> a generous Vertue? What is it but a <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> a goodneſs of Temper, a <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> or divine Principle accommo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dated to the human Nature, and reſiding
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:37402:59"/>in human Breaſts? The like might be ſaid in many other Particulars.</p>
            <p>Suppoſe alſo that the ſacred Writers themſelves do not make mention of Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neroſity under that expreſs Name, or under the ſelf-ſame Characters by which I have deſcribed it; neither will that, I conceive, juſtly prejudice what I have ſaid upon this Subject. If there be in Men ſuch Principles as Self-love and Self-eſteem, as Ambition, as Honour and Shame: If theſe Principles may and ought to be made uſe of for the purpoſes of Vertue: If the juſt uſe of theſe Principles ſerves to produce Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neroſity in Men: If Generoſity, by ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rating upon theſe Principles and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducting them rightly, be helpful to ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vance Men in Vertue and Goodneſs: If the Characters herein aſcribed to Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roſity be conſonant to the pureſt Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples of our Minds, and to the clear and undoubted Notions which wiſe Men have all along had of things: Then the main of what I have before offer'd, will not, I conceive, be ſhaken by a ſide-wind Objection. It was not, nor is it neceſſary, or indeed poſſible, that Men in all Countries or Ages of the World ſhould follow juſt the ſame
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:37402:60"/>Modes of conception or expreſſion, or the ſame Methods of Diſcourſe. There is, no doubt, a great Latitude that may be fairly taken, in the manner of diſcourſing about the particular Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues, and of referring them to certain general Principles of the rational Soul. Accordingly, we find that the Holy Writers themſelves do fall into that va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riety in this Caſe, which the nature of things ſo eaſily admits. They often va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry from one another in their Expreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and in their Methods of Diſcourſe and Exhortation upon much the ſame Subjects. They give us diverſly the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcriptions or characters of particular Vertues: Sometimes in ſuch manner as ſeems agreeable to the true nature of them, and at other times in ſuch man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner as is moſtly ſuited to the preſent Argument or Purpoſe of the Writer, or to the Principles of the Mind to which they are for that time referred. Let us for the preſent only take notice, how many ſeveral ways Vertue in general, or Religion, or Holineſs, or Goodneſs, (call it by what ſuch-like Name you will) is repreſented to us by the ſeveral Writers of the holy Books. Sometimes it is repreſented under the name and
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:37402:60"/>characters of Wiſdom, as in the Wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings of King <hi>Solomon.</hi> Sometims un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the name of Righteouſneſs (that is, Juſtice or Rectitude) as in ſeveral of the ſacred Books. Sometimes it is compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hended under the general Phraſe, <hi>The Fear of the Lord,</hi> as in many of the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred Books both of the old and new Teſtament. Sometimes under that of Love or Dilection, comprizing in it the love of God and of our Neighbour, as in ſome of the Books of the old Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and moſt of the Books of the new, particularly in the Writings of St. <hi>John</hi> and St. <hi>Paul.</hi> Sometimes under the ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral Term, Faith, exhibiting to us the ſum of our Duty, as in ſeveral Books of the new Teſtament, eſpecially in the Writings of St. <hi>Paul.</hi> If therefore the ſeveral holy Writers vary from one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in this manner, we need not won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der that others ſhould vary from them in things wherein there is naturally ſo much Latitude. Admit then that ſome one or more of the holy Writers inti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mates, that Faith is a Principle ſerving to produce in Men ſeveral particular Vertues, we muſt not think that that contradicts or excludes what is ſpoken by ſuch one or more of the holy Writers
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:37402:61"/>as intimates, that Love, or the Fear of God, are Principles ſerviceable to that end. Here are now, ſuppoſe, before our Eyes four things which may be deemed Principles of Vertue and Goodneſs; <hi>viz.</hi> Faith, Love, Fear of God, and Generoſity. But ſurely the ſaying that Faith is ſuch a Principle, does not exclude Love from being ſuch too. And ſaying that Love is ſuch a Principle, does not exclude the Fear of God from being ſuch too. And ſaying that the Fear of God is ſuch a Princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, does not exclude Generoſity from being ſuch too; becauſe they are, each of them, more or leſs ſuch. Nor on the other ſide, will Generoſity exclude the other Principles of Faith, Love, or the Fear of God, or they exclude it, any more than they exclude one another, or any more than they exclude Prudence and Sincerity (conſidered as general Principles of Vertue) or indeed any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther general Principle beſides, which ſerves for producing Vertue in Men. The Principles aforementioned may be all of them jointly and ſeverally Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples productive of Vertue. And ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordingly, to them, as ſuch, either to all of them together, or to any of them
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:37402:61"/>apart, ſeveral particular Vertues may properly be referred. And of this we have, in the caſe of Faith, a great In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance in the <hi>11th</hi> Chapter to the <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brews,</hi> where we find attributed to Faith, a great number of Vertues which diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſhed and ſignalized the Heroes and good Men in ſeveral Ages of the World. So that upon the Matter, the conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of the Style, or the manner of Writing, uſed by the holy Penmen of the Scripture, will not, I conceive, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford any juſt exception againſt what I have before offer'd, or give any occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to doubt but that Generoſity is ſuch a Principle of Vertue and Goodneſs as I pretend it is. But to ſpeak freely, why indeed ſhould we think, that none of the holy Writers take notice of the Principle of Generoſity; when we find that St. <hi>Paul</hi> gives ſo lively a deſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ption of it, in which he concludes and ſums up his other particular Exhortati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, <hi>Phil.</hi> 4.8. <hi>Finally, my Brethren,</hi> ſays he, <hi>whatſoever things are True, what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever things are Honest</hi> [or Venerable] <hi>whatſoever things are Just, whatſoever things are Pure, whatſoever things are Lovely, whatſoever things are of good Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port; if there be any Vertue, and if there
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:37402:62"/>be any Praiſe</hi> [that is, if they be Vertu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous and Praiſe-worthy] <hi>think on theſe things.</hi> And, when we likewiſe find in general, that the ſeveral Vertues which I have ſhewn do belong to its Chara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cter, are by frequent and earneſt Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepts and Exhortations inculcated upon Men throughout their Writings, tho' in other Words perhaps, or under o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Heads and Relations; I ſay, when we find the Caſe to be thus, why ſhould we think, that the holy Writers take no notice of this Principle? We need not be much concerned about a Word or Name, when we have the Thing and Subſtance. If the Thing may in the Subſtance of it be found in Scripture: Or if it be not really and materially repugnant to what is delivered there: Or if (which is all one in effect) it may be demonſtrated by rational and convincing Conſiderations, to be a good and uſeful Principle; that ought, as I take it, to content us.</p>
            <p>II. In the next place I ſhould en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour to ſhew the uſefulneſs of the Principle of Generoſity for the due Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment of our Actions. But from the Interpretation of this Principle, which I have before offer'd, we may pretty
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:37402:62"/>well diſcern that it is like to be of great uſe for that purpoſe. And this will in great meaſure ſuperſede what I intended to ſpeak under this Head; at leaſt, will oblige me to handle it with the more brevity.</p>
            <p>We find, there is a vaſt variety of Circumſtances wherein Men may be placed when they come to chuſe and act. Men fall at times under different Relations to one another; and their Caſes come to be diverſified by Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtances and Accidents emerging. By which means it comes to paſs, that they are oftentimes at a loſs how to chuſe and act, even in Caſes, which, if they were ſtrip'd of ſeveral of their Circumſtances, would ſeem plain and clear. And thus being in a kind of ſuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſe, they are many times impelled one way or other by very light Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, and often chuſe and act for the worſe. Men often encourage themſelves to the doing of what they acknowledge in general to be unlawful or unfitting, by little excuſes and pretences which they fetch from the Circumſtances of the Caſe they are in; and being by aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed and enclined to comply with their Paſſions and Intereſts, make uſe of theſe
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:37402:63"/>Arts to vindicate their Reputation with Men, or avert the checks and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proaches of their own Minds; and ſo inſenſibly beguile themſelves into baſe and vitious Actions whilſt they pretend both to know and practiſe better. So likewiſe, there are many Caſes where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in a thing, about the doing or refuſing whereof we come to deliberate, may in ſtrictneſs be lawful to be done, but peradventure may not be expedient, fitting, or honourable. Again, ſome things lie as it were between the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fines of Vertue and Vice, lawful and unlawful. A little exceſs or defect may make the Action either vertuous or vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious, as the Caſe may be. Now in ſuch Caſes as theſe, it is of mighty uſe to lay before our ſelves ſome Rules or Principles of univerſal extent, which will reach our Caſe whatever almoſt it be, and bring us under their obligation, where particular ones either would fall ſhort, or may ſeem to be leſs clear and undoubted, or are capable of being elu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded by the ſubtilty which we are wont to make uſe of for the more ſecure and uninterrupted gratification of our De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires. And ſuch a Principle is this of Generoſity: Which they that are accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtomed
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:37402:63"/>to put it in practice, ſenſibly find to be of great and univerſal influ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, and to be as well a Reſtraint upon them from committing of many things which perhaps might upon the foot of particular Vertues or Rules of Action, be deemed lawful, as likewiſe an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citement to them to the doing of many things which particular Vertues, conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered ſtrictly, or as they are ordinarily wont to be, may not abſolutely re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire.</p>
            <p>Another conſiderable uſe of this Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciple is, That it eaſily and without la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour of Thought opens it ſelf to our Minds; and ſo is always ready and at hand for our direction. It ſometimes falls out, that when we come to act, we are unreſolved whether we ſhall do a thing or not, and before we can well reſolve, are obliged to argue and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider with our ſelves (more or leſs, as the Caſe may be) and ſo come gradu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally to a Reſolution, by a train of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ductions, to the making whereof is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired ſome intention or application of Mind. And on the other ſide, it ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times falls out, that the nature of the thing before us is ſuch, that it will not give us leave to ſpend much time in de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bating
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:37402:64"/>the Matter with our ſelves, but requires an immediate Reſolution to be taken. Now it muſt needs be of great advantage to us in ſuch Caſes, to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe to our ſelves, ſome ſuch Principle or Principles, as do eaſily and inſtantly open themſelves to our Minds, and without labour of Thought ſuggeſt what is fit to be done, 'Tis eaſie to diſcern, that one conſiderable uſe of that excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent Rule, <hi>Do as you would be done unto,</hi> conſiſts in this, that it gives us a ready direction on the ſudden, and quickly clears the thing in hand from many of the Difficulties which our prepoſſeſs'd Affections or Inclinations would mix with it. For by making the Caſe our own, we quickly diſcern what we our ſelves would deſire to have done to us, and by conſequence, how we ſhould carry it to others in the ſame circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances. Thus it is with reſpect to Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neroſity. It operates by plain, ſimple and eaſie Suggeſtions: It leaves us only to reſolve upon the ſingle Point, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the thing be decent and honour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able; whether it be fit for a Man of Spirit and Temper, to do that about which we deliberate; whether, admit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting it be lawful to do the thing, it
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:37402:64"/>would not be much better and more ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable to do otherwiſe; or the like. It operates in Men upon theſe Occaſions, by ſuch a Sincerity of Mind as diſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes them to prefer that which is beſt and moſt becoming. And tho' it helps them to reſolve on the ſudden, yet it helps them to reſolve rightly. Now I believe it will be readily acknowledged, that a Principle which works this way, muſt needs be of great uſe. And this will be further confirmed to us, if we conſider the eaſineſs and advantage there is in acting by a Principle that is ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mogeneous and all of a piece, beyond what there is in being guided by a great many particular Rules, which ly broken and piece-meal in the Mind; and not having a ſtrait connexion with one another may eaſily ſlip from the Memory when they ſhould be put in practice, or if we remember them, are likely in many Caſes to be defective and inadequate. Proverbs and Maxims well applied, are profitable to ripen our experience in things, and to help us in our Practice; and particular Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepts of Vertue have their uſe: But there ſeems to be nothing more effectu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al to render the tenour of Mens Acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:37402:65"/>ſtrait, even and uniform, than a ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral Principle of the Mind that is en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tire and one; which operates without varying or mixing of Ideas; and as it cannot eaſily be abſent from the Mind when they come to act, ſo neither is it likely to prove ſhort and defective. And ſuch a one is the Principle now before us.</p>
            <p>Another conſiderable uſe of this Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciple, is, That 'tis a mighty help to Mens improvement in Vertue. I do not mean barely, that 'tis in general ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commodated to ſerve this end, as ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral other things are: But if I am not miſtaken, it has ſomething extraordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry in it, effectual for that purpoſe: Inſomuch that he who will purſue its Dictates, may promiſe himſelf ſuch im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>provements in Vertue, as are not to be expected from any other but a lively and vigorous Principle. For the truth of this I may ſafely appeal to the expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience of thoſe who have accuſtomed themſelves to act upon this Principle. But it will appear to have nothing of improbability in it, if we conſider well on the one hand the nature of Genero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity, and on the other hand the courſe and order wherein Mens cogitations
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:37402:65"/>and actions were wont to be produced and conducted, together with the Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples they naturally act upon. We ſhall not perhaps think it ſtrange, that Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roſity ſhould have this effect, if we con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider that it opens Mens Minds to great and exact Thoughts; that it ſteers and directs the Will in its right courſe; that it ſerves to repreſent Vertue as a lovely thing, and puts Men into a Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thod of doing and repeating vertuous Actions with Delight; and by that means, as alſo by exciting in them a commendable Ambition of excelling in Vertue as the moſt honourable thing in the World, engages them vehemently in the purſuit of it. But ſince there is nothing ſo likely to convince Men in this Matter, as their own tryal and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience, that is it which I ſhall prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipally recommend to them. And there is the greater encouragement to make a Tryal, becauſe they cannot reaſonably think, that, ſuppoſing it be not a help, it will be any impediment to them in a vertuous courſe; or that the meaſures it puts them into will be harſh and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>delightful, when the Principle it ſelf is ſo congenial, and ſo agreeable to the pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt and moſt uncorrupt Sentiments of their Minds.</p>
            <pb n="118" facs="tcp:37402:66"/>
            <p>In ſum. If this Principle were well purſued, there would in all appearance be a great deal more Juſtice, Order, Quiet and good Agreement in the World, than now there is. It is in its nature extreamly accommodated to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce theſe auſpicious effects. And being of a very large and extended nature, it reaches to all orders and degrees of Men. It enters into the Laws of Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture and of Nations: Which cannot well ſubſiſt without a regard to the Rules of Humanity, Decency and Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour. It mixes it ſelf with the Laws of particular Polities; and by diſpoſing Men to a regular performance of the reſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctive Duties relating to Government and Subjection, tends to preſerve that Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der and Quiet which is the laſt end of Government. Thus a Generous Prince will endeavour to adminiſter his Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment with an even and ſteady hand, to protect his Subjects ſtrenuouſly, to maintain the juſt Honour of the Crown and Faith of the Treaſury, to ſhun thoſe little Arts which are ſometimes made uſe of to amaſs Wealth, or to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>croach on the Rights of Subjects or Neighbours. He will think himſelf obliged to avoid whatever is mean, diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>honourable.
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:37402:66"/>and unbecoming his Chara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cter: And by how much he is elevated in Power and Dignity above other Men, will eſteem himſelf by ſo much the more engaged to obſerve, as near as he can, the Rules of Conduct and Honour. And on the other ſide, Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerous Subjects will not be peeviſh and ill-natured towards their Prince, or raſhly put on his Actions an unfavour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able Conſtruction: They will not en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vy him for his Greatneſs, or his juſt Rights and Prerogatives: They will chearfully render him his Tribures and Duties: In a word, they will honour his Perſon and obey his Commands; and where they cannot <hi>bona fide</hi> in Law or Conſcience do the latter, they will meekly ſubmit and pay a Deference to his Authority, tho' they cannot actively obey it; chuſing rather to ſuffer in their own private Concerns, than by oppoſition to affront their Prince, or diſturb the repoſe and tranquility of the Publick. Thus the Principle of Generoſity is of great benefit to the State.</p>
            <p>And ſo it is likewiſe to the Church. It will diſpoſe the Clergy to be Manly, Grave and Diſcreet in diſcharging the
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:37402:67"/>Offices of their Function; to exerciſe Diſcipline with a Courage and Exact<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, mixed with Temper and Mode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration; to be vigilant and careful in looking to their reſpective Charges; to perform the Offices of divine Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip with ſuch a Decency, Order and Devotion, as may be ſuitable to the nature of the thing, and helpful to main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain it in that juſt eſteem which it ought to have in the World; to ſhut out of their Diſcourſes and Inſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, precarious Hypotheſes, pious Frauds, Pedantry and Oſtentation of pretended Learning, indecent Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſions, and whatever is diſagreeable to true Reaſon and the holy Scriptures; to avoid Simoniacal Arts and mean Compliances; and, in a word, what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever is really unbecoming their Order. And on the other ſide, a Generous Man of the Laity, will reſpect and eſteem the Clergy for their Office-ſake; he will neither envy them their Revenues nor defraud them of their Dues; he will cover their Faults, and candidly receive their Inſtructions; he will not for ſlight and trivial pretences make or countenance a Separation from the Church under which he was born, or
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:37402:67"/>break its Communion and diſturb its Peace for the ſake of things confeſſedly harmleſs and indifferent in themſelves; and as he is not in his Temper incli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable to oppoſe his Governors, ſo he has no Temptation either to think him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf exempt from their Authority, or to imagine that a thing indifferent in it ſelf can meerly by the command of a Superiour be rendred unlawful. In ſhort, Generoſity opens Mens Minds to ſuch Sentiments as diſpoſe them to Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſty, Peaceableneſs and Goodneſs of Temper: Which cannot but be of great Benefit both in Church and State.</p>
            <p>But Generoſity is alſo of great uſe to the Publick, by its ſuitableneſs to influ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence all Orders and Degrees of Men. It is indeed a Principle in which the No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bility and Gentry ſeem to have in ſome ſort a more peculiar Intereſt than other Men. Yet there is no Man, tho' of mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner Fortunes, but he is more or leſs con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerned in it. All Men have equally a natural freedom of acting, and are, as far as relates immediately to the Laws of Vertue, equally engaged to uſe that Freedom rightly; being equally enti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuled to the Rewards of uſing it right<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly,
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:37402:68"/>and ſubject to the Puniſhments which enſue the Abuſe of it. And ſo alſo all Men who are not fallen from the Rights of the human Nature, are intereſſed in that Reputation and E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteem which is due to vertuous and worthy Actions; and are concerned to maintain a Reputation accordingly. However there ſeem to be additional Obligations lying upon the Nobility and Gentry, to act upon the true Principles of Honour, which affect them more peculiarly than other Men: The honourable Style and Titles that belong to them, as well as the Emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nence of their Station and Degree ſhould put them continually in Mind of acting upon theſe Principles, and of endeavouring to ſurpaſs others therein. For what can be more diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>agreeable, than for a Gentleman or Man of Quality, to be of a pitiful ſordid Spirit, to be rough and ill<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bred, and deſtitute of all ſenſe of Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour and Vertue. And on the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary, it muſt needs be a great Orna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to ſuch Perſons to have that firmneſs and rectitude of Mind, that candour and goodneſs of Temper,
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:37402:68"/>that Civility and decent Addreſs, and that conformity to the Laws of Deco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum, Honour and Vertue; which are Properties of Generoſity. And herein, thoſe of ancient Families, and thoſe of later Creation, are both con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerned. He that is Noble by De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcent, has great Obligations to ſpur him on to Generous and Worthy Acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons: He has the Obligations that ariſe from the Dignity in which he is placed, and likewiſe the Example of his brave Anceſtors; which ought to inſpire him with a juſt emulation of their Vertue, and make him afraid of incurring the Character of Degene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous, — <hi>Magnorum indignus Avo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum.</hi> And he that has acquired No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bleſs by his own Merit, has, not only the Obligations which ariſe from the Dignity of his preſent Station, but al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo thoſe concurrent Reaſons which ſhould engage him to act ſuitably to the Character he has gained; leſt he ſhould afterwards forfeit by Ignoble Actions, the Eſteem and Dignity which he had before ſo worthily ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired, and ſhould as it were degene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate from himſelf. Theſe are Conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derations
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:37402:69"/>which as they more particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larly affect the Nobility and Gentry, ſo they ought to be of great weight with them. It is true, that the moſt ſolid Obligations of all, to Genero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity, are thoſe which reſult from the Nature of Things, and which con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern all Men equally of whatever de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree. For 'tis undoubtedly more ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable to imitate God Almighty himſelf, than the moſt vertuous and excellent Men that ever were: And there are ſtronger Reaſons to engage Men to a generous and vertuous Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haviour, which may be fetch'd from the nature of Vertue it ſelf, than any that ariſe barely from the conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of ſecular Dignity and Emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nence, or the Example of Anceſtors. Nevertheleſs, where there are concur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent Reaſons, ſome of higher, others of lower Obligation, they ought all to be allowed their juſt force, and all made uſe of to engage Men to honourable and vertuous Courſes, ſince all the Arguments of both ſorts which can be brought, are commonly found hardly effectual for that pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe. But as Generoſity is a Princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:37402:69"/>of acting, very much becoming Perſons of elevated Character and great Fortunes; and they have addi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tional Arguments above many other Men, to engage them to the practice of it: So it is eaſie to diſcern, that the practice of it is like to be more illu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrious in them, and more beneficial to the World, than the practice of the ſame in Men of inferiour Condition. The Vices of great Men are more conſpicuous than thoſe of meaner Folks: And ſo are their Vertues. Their Character and Station is more Publick, and their Example both of greater force and of more diffuſed Influence: And the greater is their Power of doing either good or hurt, They have commonly many Tenants, Clyents and Dependents, to whom their Generous Behaviour is like to bring great Advantage, and the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary, great Miſchief and Damage: And perhaps the well or ill-being in the World, of theſe People, muſt be in great meaſure owing to the gener<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous or ungenerous diſpoſition of their Patrons. So that it muſt needs be of very diffuſive Benefit, for Men who
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:37402:70"/>have high Characters or great Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands, who are Governours of Ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritories, or Lords of great Demeans, or who have great Offices and Entruſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments in the State, and in Proportion, for others of leſſer Quality or Power, to be of a true and generous Temper. And this will be, not only of great Ornament, but likewiſe of great uſe to themſelves. It will gain them the Affection and Eſteem of their Depen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dants and Neighbours, and likewiſe their Prayers and good Wiſhes; it will give them Power and Sway in their Countries; it will engage all that know them to ſtand by them, and render them all the good Offices they can: In ſhort, it will procure them the ſatisfaction and pleaſure of Mind that attends generous and worthy Acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons in this Life, and the Rewards of Vertue in the future Life.</p>
            <p>It would moreover be of great Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage to the Publick, if Men in their ſeveral Profeſſions and Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployments would purſue this Princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple more exactly. And the more re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putable a Mans Profeſſion is, he has in a ſort the greater Obligation upon
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:37402:70"/>him ſo to do. Thus, for Inſtance, a Generous Lawyer would think it di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhonourable to betray a Cauſe he is entruſted in; to plead in a Cauſe, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter he is fully ſatisfied 'tis unjuſt, with that warmth and application which is due only to a juſt one; to give Advice with a regard rather to his own Profit, than either to the Law or the Suitors Benefit; to blow the Coals of Contention, or encour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age litigious and frivolous Suits which he knows before-hand will be of no Fruit to the Party; or in more juſt or colourable Cauſes to ſpend the Clients Mony unneceſſarily in skir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſhing and playing of Prizes about Matters wherein Juſtice or the Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits of the Cauſe are nothing con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerned; to apply the Law to the contriving or defending of Frauds and Oppreſſions, or pervert it to the hurt or ruin of the innocent and honeſt Perſon whom it is or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dained to protect. Theſe things, and ſuch like, a Generous Man, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther he be of higher or lower Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racter in the Profeſſion, will think himſelf obliged to avoid as diſho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:37402:71"/>nourable and baſe. And the ſame Principle will influence the Phyſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tian and Men of other Profeſſions, in their reſpective Employments. And likewiſe the Merchant and Tradeſman in his Dealings and Commerce. It would be a means to reſtrain Men from the injurious Arts of Monopoly and Exaction, from Lying, Diſſembling and other inſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dious and ill Practices that are too often uſed in buying and ſelling. And as the ſeveral ill Practices be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore mentioned, are diſhonourable in themſelves, contrary to the Rules of Sincerity and Juſtice, and prejudici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al to the good Order and Proſperi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of the Publick: So the Vertues oppoſite thereunto, which Generoſity is ſuited to produce, are both ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent in themſelves, and likewiſe of great benefit to the Publick.</p>
            <p>Nor is there indeed any Body of ſo inferiour a Station in the Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth, but what is capable of act<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, in ſome meaſure, by this Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciple. The meaneſt Artificers and Countrymen have a Reputation as well as other Men, and are concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:37402:71"/>to preſerve it inviolate. They are all under the Laws of Vertue and Decorum. They have all a Free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of Nature, and can reſolve to uſe it for the beſt Purpoſes. And ſometimes are found to act upon bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter and nobler Principles, than Men of Character and Education. It muſt be confeſs'd, that Generoſity does not conſiſt in bearing the Port of a Gentleman, or making a Figure in the World. It is compatible with all Conditions of Human Life. And is indeed more effectually demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrated by ſubmitting to a mean For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune for the ſake of Honeſty and Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue, than by ſeeking a higher Chara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cter or Station at the Price of good Conſcience or Diſcretion. It is ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſable by all Men in their ſeveral Degrees, whether they be in higher or lower Capacity; and ſerves to diſtinguiſh Men by their Minds and Spirits, rather than by their external Character or Station. Particularly, it may be exerciſed in the ſtate of Marriage or ſingle Life, of Maſter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip or Service, of Travel or Reſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, of Plenty or Penury; in Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:37402:72"/>Judicial or Miniſterial, in Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployments Civil or Military, in Peace or in War, in Victory or Defeat, in Honour or Diſgrace, in Health or Sickneſs, in Safety or Danger. It is of uſe to preſerve Peace and good Underſtanding between Domeſticks and Kinsfolks, between Neighbours and Townſmen, and People that have mutual Intercourſe; by engaging Men to that Civility, Complaiſance and Decency of Deportment, which is of great force to prevent Quarrels or Miſ-underſtandings, and the ill Conſequences of them; by deterring Men from a ſordid or provoking Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage towards one another; by cure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing or preventing that Envy and Ill<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nature which too often happen be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween Men of the ſame Callings or of the ſame Families or Neighbour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hoods; and which ſometimes produce miſchievous Effects. It will help to give a Sweetneſs and Ornament to Converſation: And make Friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhips and Correſpondencies delight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful, orderly and laſting. In a word, there is no State of Life, or Relation that Men ſtand in to one another,
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:37402:72"/>which excludes the exerciſe of it. Thus it is very ample and extended in its Influence, and helps Men to govern their Actions in ſuch manner as is very conducive to preſerve Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue, Order, Quiet and good Agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment amongſt Men. As to ſeveral other particular Uſes of this Princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, they may, many of them, be ſo evidently collected from what has been ſpoken in the Deſcription and Interpretation of it, which I am not willing to repeat; and others may be ſo eaſily ſupplied from any Mans own Obſervation; that I think it need<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs to enter upon detailing them. So much then for the Uſefulneſs of this Principle.</p>
            <p>But after all, if any Man, upon comparing the Temper of Mind and Courſe of Action of thoſe who are or paſs for Generous Men, with the Deſcription which I have given of Generoſity, ſhould pretend that Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roſity, as I have deſcribed it, looks rather like an airy Idea than a thing practicable by Mankind; ſince it would be hard (if not impoſſible) to find a Man endued with all thoſe
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:37402:73"/>Qualities which I have aſcribed to it: I ſay, if any Man ſhould object in this manner, he may pleaſe to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve, that I do not ſay, he cannot be a Generous Man who has not eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry particular Qualification which I have aſcribed or which may be aſcrib<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to that Character. A Man may, no doubt, be a Generous and Vertu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Man, though he be not perfect in Generoſity and Vertue. The Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bits of the Mind are capable of ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral degrees, or receive (as they ſpeak) <hi>Magis &amp; Minus.</hi> There is confeſſed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly a great deal of difference between Vertue conſidered formally or in its pure Nature, and conſidered ſubje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctively or under that Allay in which it is wont to appear in human Acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons. It were indeed much to be wiſh'd, that Mankind could as eaſily expreſs the Purity and Sublimity of Vertue in their Spirits and Actions, as they can repreſent it in Words and Deſcriptions. But this is not to be expected. For my part, I am as ready as any one, to acknowledge the Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>becillity of our Nature, ſince I find ſo many ſenſible Proofs of it in o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:37402:73"/>Men, but particularly in my ſelf. And, I believe, it is a ſubject of great Grief to thoſe who ſincerely aſpire after Vertue, to find ſo many Obſtructions and Impediments in their Progreſs, ariſing from their own Nature: To find themſelves divided as it were againſt themſelves, ſo that whilſt one part of them is enclined to make its Efforts after Vertue, ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther part of them retards and hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders by its revulſive Motions. This is the conflict of the Fleſh and Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, which gives Men ſo many diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culties, and renders their practice of Vertue ſo feeble and imperfect. But as this ſhews only the Imperfection of our Nature, ſo it can be no juſt Argument againſt the excellency of this or any other Vertue conſidered in it ſelf. If then we would take an Idea of any Vertue, we muſt not take it barely from the practice of particular Men, or the feeble Repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentations which they are wont to give of it in their Spirits and Acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, but from that and from the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of Vertue it ſelf together. We are to conſider the nature of things,
<pb n="134" facs="tcp:37402:74"/>and to frame a Notion of the excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lency of the Principles of our Minds by the conſideration of their abſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted Nature, and of their Confor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity to that Exemplar of Perfection which is in the divine Mind. If therefore we find the Characters of Generoſity agreeable to the nobleſt and divineſt Principles of our Minds, in conformity to that original Perfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction which is in the divine Nature it ſelf (to which all Vertues and good Qualities that are in Men, are in their meaſure and degree conforma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and correſpondent; otherwiſe they could not be ſuch:) We cannot reaſonably deny it to be in it ſelf of that Excellency and Uſefulneſs which I have mentioned, how faint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly or imperfectly ſoever it may be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hibited in the Spirits and Practice of particular Men. But it ought to be thought ſufficient, that all the Chara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cters which I have attributed to it, are to be found upon ſome ones or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers of that Body of great and good Men which have been or are in the World; and conſequently have had, and now have, a real Exiſtence. From
<pb n="135" facs="tcp:37402:74"/>hence then we may conclude, that there is in reality ſuch a Principle, and that it is in ſome degree attain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able by us. And the more excellent a Principle it is in it ſelf, we ought in reaſon the more earneſtly to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour to attain as great a Perfection in it as 'tis poſſible for us: Not faint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing though we cannot make good in our Spirits and Actions all the Chara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cters of it, but endeavouring to make good as many of them as we are able; and labouring throughout the courſe of our Life (which will be a noble Ambition) to make continually further Advances.</p>
            <p>Having thus given a Deſcription of Generoſity, I think it ſuperfluous to uſe Arguments to engage Men to the Love and Practice of it. If it be of ſo lovely and excellent a Nature, as I have ſet it forth to be, that is the moſt forcible Argument in the World, why we ſhould endeavour after it. One need not take pains to incite Men to love a beautiful Object; they do it naturally, and cannot help it. Demonſtrating that a thing is ſuch, is beyond all the collateral Arguments
<pb n="136" facs="tcp:37402:75"/>of Perſuaſion that can be uſed. If in the proceſs of this Diſcourſe, I have done that with reſpect to Generoſity, there will be no need of further Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuaſions: And if I have not, Perſuaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons would be inſignificant.</p>
            <p>III. In regard, therefore, Genero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity is a thing ſo excellent in its Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, and ſo beneficial in its uſe, 'tis like to be worth our Pains to enquire, How it may be acquired, or after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards improved in our Minds. Now when I ſpeak of acquiring it, I do not ſuppoſe that there is any Man, by Nature, totally void of it, or at leaſt of ſome Prediſpoſition to it. All Men have the Seeds and Rudi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of it ſo far as they have a ſenſe of Good and Evil, Decency and Indecency, Honour and Shame. But ſince thoſe Rudiments cannot pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perly, of themſelves, give Men the denomination of Generous; for no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing can do that, but ſome degree of the habit of Generoſity: He who would acquire that Character, muſt improve thoſe Rudiments to that de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree, at leaſt, which may be effectual
<pb n="137" facs="tcp:37402:75"/>to denominate him ſuch. Now to diſcover how this may be done, there is not, I conceive, need of any ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinary Art. The thing is plain and obvious to any Mans Under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding.</p>
            <p>Firſt, therefore, we muſt addreſs our ſelves in a due manner to God Almighty, beſeeching him to beſtow upon us this Vertue. And, Second<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, we muſt firmly and maturely re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolve to do all that we can poſſibly to attain it. The Conſideration, that God Almighty is the Soveraign Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor and Giver of all Vertues, ſhews the neceſſity of the former: And the Conſideration, that Men cannot or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinarily become Vertuous or Happy, without their own Choice and Endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour, ſhews the neceſſity of the lat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter. And indeed the reaſonableneſs and neceſſity of doing theſe two Things is ſo evident, that I think it needleſs either to inſiſt upon prove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it, or to uſe Arguments to engage Men to put them in practice. But it muſt be obſerved, that theſe two ought to go hand in hand. And both muſt be performed with that Sincerity
<pb n="138" facs="tcp:37402:76"/>of Mind which is neceſſary upon ſo juſt an occaſion. As for what relates to our own Endeavours, the Method we take in other Caſes, will ſerve in this. If we would acquire a Habit of Juſtice, Temperance, or the like Vertues: We ſtedfaſtly reſolve, and excite our ſelves, to perform thoſe Offices which pertain to Juſtice, Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perance, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and endeavour to avoid the contrary Vices: If we offend, we renew our good Reſolutions, and with doubled care and diligence en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour to put them in Execution. The like we muſt do in this Caſe. And herein we have this further En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couragement, that the ſame Methods which ſerve for acquiring this Habit, will likewiſe ſerve for our improve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in it. But more particularly, let us conſider briefly, in what manner our Endeavours upon this occaſion may be exerted.</p>
            <p>Firſt; becauſe we find it natural to Mankind to act agreeably to the No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions which they have conceived of things: And becauſe Men cannot Chuſe, nor by conſequence Act, right<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, till they can competently diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſh
<pb n="139" facs="tcp:37402:76"/>between things, and know what is fit to be choſen and what is to be refuſed: It is neceſſary, therefore, that we endeavour in the firſt place to poſſeſs our Minds with juſt Sentiments concerning the nature of Things; par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticularly, concerning the Differences between Good and Evil, Decent and Indecent, Honourable and Diſhonour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able. So alſo, becauſe it is found by experience, that there are many things which Men will not ſet about in good earneſt, till ſuch time as they are con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinced that they are under ſome Obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation to the doing of them, or that it is for their Honour or Intereſt to do them: It is neceſſary, that we repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent to our Minds with all the force and perſpicuity poſſible, thoſe Conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derations which demonſtrate, as well the honourable and becoming nature of Vertue and its happy Conſequen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, as likewiſe the firm and indiſpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſable Obligation we are under, to act according to the Rules which it pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribes. And, becauſe, on the other hand, it is found by experience, that 'tis of great uſe to reſtrain Men from the Commiſſion or Practice of ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral
<pb n="140" facs="tcp:37402:77"/>things, to convince them that they ought not to do thoſe things, and that the doing of them will be both very Pernicious and very Diſhonourable to them: It ſeemeth neceſſary, that we likewiſe repreſent to our Minds, with all the force and perſpicuity poſſible, thoſe Conſiderations which ſerve to make us ſenſible, that Vice is really Baſe and Diſhonourable, that it draws after it the bittereſt and moſt pernici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Conſequences that can be imagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, and that we are under the moſt ſolid Obligations in the World, to refuſe and avoid it with all our Power. And this is to be done ſo frequently, that the wholeſome Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſions we draw from theſe Conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations may make a deep Impreſſion upon our Minds, and beget in us an habitual and immoveable Conviction of the reaſonableneſs and neceſſity of acting accordingly. Having, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, opened our Minds to a juſt and exact Conſideration of the true na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of Things, and thereupon form<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed certain general Judgments or Rules by which we may conduct our Acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons ſo, as to ehuſe that which is Good,
<pb n="141" facs="tcp:37402:77"/>Decent and Honourable, and to ſhun and avoid the contrary; and even to prefer that which is more Good, De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent and Honourable, before that which is leſs ſo: It will only remain, that we firmly and adviſedly reſolve with our ſelves to go, in all Caſes, as near as we can, by thoſe Rules; and whether we be more or leſs knowing, endeavour to act according to the beſt of our Skill and Knowledge. And by this means we ſhall be put in a way of making the right and beſt uſe both of our Underſtandings and our Wills, which are the two great Springs from whence our Actions do pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed.</p>
            <p>But, further; becauſe it is found, that Men are naturally bent to deſire and proſecute thoſe things which ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear to be lovely and amiable; It ſeemeth proper, that we ſhould like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe take all fit Occaſions to contem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plate and repreſent to our ſelves the amiable nature of this Vertue of Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neroſity; that as it is very beautiful in it ſelf, ſo it may appear, in a lively manner ſuch to our Minds. A Beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty will not Charm, if concealed or un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>obſerved.
<pb n="142" facs="tcp:37402:78"/>Nor will Generoſity ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear to us Lovely, as it is, unleſs we turn the Eyes of our Minds towards it. It is neceſſary, therefore, in this Caſe, that we apply our ſelves as well to conſider the Characters of Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neroſity in the Theory, as likewiſe to obſerve, how beautiful it appears to be in ſuch as exerciſe it in a juſt man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner; what a Charm and Engagement it carries with it; how Decent, how Venerable, how Agreeable to our beſt Thoughts, it is. By this means we ſhall be inſpired with the Love and Admiration of it, and conſequently be engaged to purſue it with Vigour.</p>
            <p>In a word; though it be of good uſe to ſet before our ſelves, in general, good and wholſome Rules of acting, and to make general Reſolutions of purſuing them, and to ſtrengthen thoſe Reſolutions with ſuch Conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations and Motives as are proper for that purpoſe: Yet it ſeems material to be obſerved, that this will hardly be effectual, unleſs we likewiſe enure our ſelves, actually to put in execution the Reſolutions which we make, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce thoſe Rules into Practice in par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular
<pb n="143" facs="tcp:37402:78"/>Caſes. Experience ſhews, how heedleſs and unvigilant Men are wont to be, and how ineffectual and ill uſory their general Reſolutions often prove: Inſomuch, that for want of confirming themſelves in the Habits of Vertue by particular and repeated Acts, they ſometimes fall into the contrary Habits of Vice, and undo all the good Reſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutions they had formerly made. It is found, that Habits are gained by the frequent repeating of particular Acts, and are confirmed and improved by Uſe and Practice; nor can indeed long ſubſiſt without it. And ſo in particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar is the Habit of Generoſity. And, therefore, we muſt of neceſſity enure and accuſtom our ſelves to particular Acts of Generoſity, if we deſire to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire the Habit of it, or to continue or improve in that Character.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="errata">
            <pb facs="tcp:37402:79"/>
            <head>ERRATA.</head>
            <p>PAge 11. line, 12. add 1. p. 13. l. 5. for <hi>Perfections</hi> read <hi>Perceptions.</hi> p 14. l. 8. after [eſteem] make a; p. 28. l. 8. r. <hi>com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounded.</hi> p. 33. l. 24, after <hi>that,</hi> add <hi>it.</hi> p. 36. l. 13. r. <hi>make ſuch uſe of it, as that it may,</hi> p. 42. l. 25. f. <hi>undertake</hi> r. <hi>undervalue.</hi> p. 65. l. 24. f. <hi>on</hi> r. <hi>in.</hi> and l. 25. f. <hi>in</hi> r. <hi>on.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
